In an inn, near the entrance of one of the valleys of the Giant Mountains, several peasants met together one evening, and after having made themselves merry over trencher and flagon, began to tease a young bashful looking lad, who had taken his station behind the stove, and looked like a travelling scholar. The youth had been observed to betray some symptoms of fear, when, by chance, the name of the whimsical Number Nip fell out in the discourse of the peasants, and the merry rustics took a malicious pleasure in heightening his alarm by telling story after story of the far famed Lord of the Mountain.

The young stranger made several ineffectual attempts to change the subject of conversation. At last one of the peasants, willing to display his wit, thus addressed him: “Now, my young lily-faced master, as you look somewhat like a travelling scholar, methinks it would be but wise and fitting in you to draw some good moral from all our stories; and, I suppose, one is quite as good as another to you in this respect.”

“Oh,” replied the student, “I would willingly comply with what you suggest; but I am only afraid, that, were I to try to turn every thing you tell me to such good account, you might find some cause of blame in me; and I am very timid.”

The peasants laughed aloud at so modest a speech, but promised to listen to all that he might say without taking offence, and to pay his reckoning for him besides, if he should be able to deduce some profitable moral from every story that they might tell him of Number Nip. So one of the company thus began:

“Once upon a time a certain man took his way up the Giant Mountain with the special design of meeting with Number Nip, and begging from the Spirit the gift of a little magical book which should teach him how to rule the weather according as it pleased him, how to transform himself into any shape, how to bewitch his neighbour’s cattle, and, in short, how to perform a great many very strange and surprising tricks. Well, after looking about him for a long time, he at last perceived Number Nip, in the form of a little, old, decrepit man, seated in the mouth of a cave, who gave him such a little book as he described, and the impudent varlet took his way homewards again in great joy. But on the following morning, when he opened the little book, thinking to do some strange cantrip with it, lo and behold, every trace of the wonderful lines and figures which Number Nip had shown him in it the day before had vanished, and instead of a nicely written book, he had nothing but a parcel of worthless green leaves in his hand, with no other trace of figures or writing upon them than the shapeless lines and strokes which the hand of Nature has drawn upon the leaves of every tree and bush and shrub!”

The peasants were highly pleased with this story, and thought the novice in necromancy well-punished for his daring; but at last they asked the student to treat them with the moral of the story, and he, after a little reflection, began to recite the following strophe in a low voice:

“He who famous deeds would do,
First must humbly listen to
School-dame Nature’s teaching, and
Read the books which she has penn’d;—
Sealed these books to vulgar eyes,
Open only to the wise.
Will surely soar to wisdom’s height;
But he who nought therein can see,
A rustic clown for aye will be.”

“Sirrah, I think you are mocking us!” exclaimed the peasant who had told the story, in great wrath.

“Yes, yes,” murmured another, “the fellow is taking his sport off us. I am sure none of us could ever read what was written on the leaf of a tree; and therefore are we to understand that we are all blockheads?”

“Now, you see, my respected friends,” replied the student, “you see how instantly you begin to quarrel with me! Would that I had remained silent; but I trusted to your promise!”

The rustics, thus reminded of their pledge, promised to observe it, and another of them proceeded thus:

“Now, my good master student, I will tell you a story about one of your own sort of folks, for it is but fit that we should have our joke in turn at your expense. One of your scholar-kind of people was one day crossing the mountain; he wore a sword dangling at his side, and carried a guitar in his hand, and ever as he stalked along, he shouted some of his love songs into the blue air.”

“Nay, then he was a great deal bolder than I am,” interrupted the youth.

“I think so too, sir,” replied the peasant. “But as my gentleman marched onwards, what think you befell him? A young spark, whom he took for a student like himself, comes up to him, and, after talking all sorts of learned stuff, takes his guitar, pretending that he was going to teach him a very pretty song. But no sooner has he got hold of the instrument than up he jumps with it, faster than any squirrel, into a very high tree, and there he sits among the green branches, and sings and plays away quite at his ease! At first this nimble-footed magician chose such merry and pleasant songs, that the poor fellow at the foot of the tree stood and listened as if to a nightingale; but all at once he changed both time and tune and song, and began to bawl out such scurvy rhymes that his companion at the foot of the tree called out to him, in great wrath, to descend and restore his guitar, which was never intended for such a blockhead’s hands. But the fellow in the tree became more outrageous than ever, and began to make such provoking songs about the poor scholar and his sweatheart, that my gentleman unable any longer to contain himself, drew his sword, and leaped a yard high in the air, calling on the scoundrel musician to come down and defend his life. Thereupon an ugly visage grinned down upon him from the tree, and at the same moment the guitar fell at his feet with a crash as if it had been shivered into a thousand pieces. The poor scholar swooned away when he beheld the hideous visage above him; but when he recovered and found his guitar lying unhurt at his side, he concluded that he had met with Number Nip himself; and from that hour he has never set foot again on the Giant Mountains.”

“Faith, I can well believe that!” exclaimed one of the group, highly delighted with the story of the unlucky minstrel.—“And I think that fellow would sing as little as possible all his lifetime afterwards!” remarked another.—“Nay, for that very reason,” began a third, “I half suspect we have got the unfortunate minstrel in proper person behind the stove there!”

“Do you really think so?” said the student, looking very thoughtful and pensive. “But I am still owing you the moral, my good friends. Give attention, it runs somewhat thus:

“Let the youth to whom belong
The envied arts of verse and song,
Shunning jest and idle word
Use his gifts to praise the Lord.
But should he in some evil hour
Pervert the heaven-descended power—
Sure the minstrel’s hand is free
And the strain may changed be,
While the chords unbroken still
Wake to music at his will!
Has thy babbling tongue revealed
Secrets thou shouldst have concealed,—
Erring minstrel, let this be
A lasting lesson unto thee,
And henceforth more discreet and wise,
Veil thy love’s charms from vulgar eyes.”

“Indeed!” exclaimed one of the peasants. “If that is not meant for us, nothing in the world is! ‘Vulgar eyes!’ Well, well, I see through your learning, master student, and warn you once for all to let us alone with your quizzing.”

“Never mind, man!” shouted another of the group. “I say, never mind. If he knows Greek, surely we are no blockheads!”

This observation kept down the rising wrath of the rest, and the assurances and protestations of the student that he meant nothing personal to such honourable gentlemen, completely mollified their resentment, and it was resolved to carry on the jest.

“A man of high rank,” began one of the company, “becoming dissatisfied with one of his acquaintances, resolved to send him a very insulting and threatening letter. But somehow or other—nobody can tell how—Number Nip took hold of the pen with which he was writing, and so guided it, that he wrote just the very contrary of what he meant to express. Thus, for example, instead of writing, ‘Thou art a perjured rascal, unworthy to loose the shoe-ties of an honourable man like me,’ he actually wrote, ‘I am a perjured rascal, unworthy to loose the shoe-ties of an honourable man like thee.’ Consequently instead of a letter of insult and provocation, as was meant, the nobleman’s enemy received a pitiful and humble confession from him, and so the poor man of quality was laughed and sneered at by every body for a long time afterwards.”

The company were highly pleased with this story, and some of them jeeringly besought the student to tell them all that such a funny letter might contain; for—they added with affected humility—they were such poor ignorant creatures that none of them had great skill in the mysteries of letter-writing.

“Listen to me, gentlemen,” began the student. “I shall, with your leave, propound you something on my side, and, for once at least, the moral shall be a brief one. Here it is in two words:

You with the torch, let your neighbour alone,
Lest in singing his fingers, you scorch your own.

Now, my worthies, would you desire to witness my trick? It needs no learned clerk’s skill to understand it!”

“Go on! Go on!” shouted the half-tipsy peasants.

The student stept round the company, and drew some signs in the air with his finger before the mouth of each individual while he recited the following singular verses

The tongue and the cat
Are sly to overreach;
Fit couple they make,
Slaying each after each,
One with its teeth,
And one with its speech.

The tongue and the cat
Are not sly enough;
There’s a spell that has power
To give both a rebuff!
Come chatter, dear tongue,
Your true tipsy stuff!”

The peasants were much amused at so great an increase of boldness in the student’s demeanour; and attributing it to the influence of the liquor, they thought that if they could only get the fellow drunk they would have rare sport with him. So, when the youth had resumed his seat behind the stove, one of them presented him with a full bumper, saying:

“Now, courage, my hearty! I must drink till I measure my length on the ground, or all will not be well with me.”

“Do as you please,” replied the student very calmly.

“Yes,” responded the peasant, with assumed sternness, “you may do as you please,—quite as you please,—and if ever the very thought should cross my mind of preventing you, may I be soundly basted with your staff!”

“John,” exclaimed his comrades, laughing aloud, “what are you saying!”

Hereupon one of them, who was esteemed the wisest of their number, began with an air of great gravity: “Leave my honest friend, John, in peace! What is it that you are making such a fuss about? Had such a thing happened to me, who, you well know, am the stupidest blockhead amongst you, you might well laugh at it; but John is a wiser fellow, and you may well leave him to his own guidance.”

The company stared upon one another: “Children,” began another of the circle, “it is my grave belief you have bewitched this young student by sinful and wicked means.”

“I thought so from the very beginning!” added a third; and all broke out into a furious burst of passion, exclaiming: “Nothing shall prevent the student from beating each and all of us till he leave not a sound bone in our bodies! We have used him vilely! But wait a little; we shall be repaid in our own coin.”

Thus matters went on; the peasants fully conscious that their lips gave utterance to the express contrary of what they meant, grew more and more incensed at each impotent attempt to speak their wrath, and were about to rush in upon the magician who had so bewitched them, when suddenly the lights were extinguished, and the peasants could only discern the glaring eyes of an enormous owl which sat before them on the table. In their terror they made a simultaneous rush to the door; but outlet they could find none, while in their distress they kept shouting aloud in the most lamentable tone: “We are sorcerers! We are goblins! The student might have known this from the very beginning!”

Then the owl spoke to them in a grim voice: “Keep yourselves easy, my beloved friends; there is no occasion for alarm. Here I am, quite comfortable I assure you, and just as much the master as ever. Do you not know, my dears, that the owl is the bird of wisdom? Well, a student is just such a bird, and a very merry bird he is too, I assure ye, and there is no occasion for any great change amongst us. To be sure our situation is a little altered; just a trifle of a few hundred miles have we, my worthies, sunk down into the ground. But this should be a matter of no uneasiness to you, for I am Number Nip, and this is one of my palace halls. Don’t you see the roof above you is solid gold, and the rafters are entire diamonds! Come set to work and enrich yourselves for life!”

Stimulated by conflicting terror and avarice, the peasants now began to climb up upon one another’s shoulders to get at the diamonds. The innkeper himself was foremost of the band; and in a short time, so dexterously had they used their knives, the sky with its sparkling stars appeared through the gap in the roof. The brilliance of the heavenly gems gap only excited their cupidity to a higher pitch,—one loaded himself with a huge rafter,—another groaned under the load of rushes and straw he had piled upon his own back,—and jealousy and anger had their full play amongst them, each one striving to appropriate to himself the largest portion of what appeared inestimable treasures.

When the first ray of the morning-sun shone upon them, they found themselves standing on the roof of the inn, each one loaded with an immense weight of rafters and rushes; and it may easily be conceived how silly they looked in such a situation,—the more especially as some of their neighbours, who were going a-field to the hay-making at an early hour, got their eyes upon them, and indulged in some hearty jokes at their expense.

It is said that from that time, the innkeeper and his companions, evinced great politeness towards all strangers, and treated travelling students with especial respect.

“Shut the door, Margery, my dear,” said her old grandfather, “and bolt it too very carefully. Our young gentlemen students are about to jubilate in the streets to night, as neighbour Schwertfeger informs me, and it may be better for quiet people who occupy the ground floor, like us, to be something upon our guard. Meanwhile, I will look to the window shutters; it is already getting quite dark, and it is high time to light a candle.”

“But how will our old lodger find his way in, then, grandfather?” said the little maiden; “you know he is still out among the pine trees, and wandering about the old heathen monuments and tombs.”

“Let him rummage there, as long as he pleases, child, we cannot hinder him. And he may please, likewise, to wait awhile before the door, when he comes; for, to say truth, I do not like his ways at all, and I am sorry that I ever promised the professor, on taking the house, not to turn the strange lodger out of doors.”

“Oh, grandfather! it was surely hard enough upon poor Mr. Professor to be obliged to leave his nice family house, all owing to his wicked creditors; and it vexes me to think of it. For Mr. Professor always looks so kind and pleasant, and not so old as the other professors; then he can tell so many fine stories of by-gone times, which though they almost make one’s hair stand on end, are very pretty to hear. And as to the strange lodger, he is, perhaps, much better in his heart, than he sometimes appears to me.”

“May be so, child; but I wish I had stayed in my own little house. Whenever I go past it, I feel a kind of sinking at my heart; it was much pleasanter there.”

“Yet I think you used to complain and groan more there, than you do here, grandfather.”

“How can you make that out, Margery? You know I only removed just to please good Mr. Professor. I wish from my heart he had continued to live here instead of us; at all events he would have paid no house rent! yet he would not listen to the idea for a moment; but now, my dear, let us think of the door! see that it is made quite fast!”

Little Margery did as her grandfather bade her; she turned the key three times in the lock; slipped the bolts as far as they would go, and then both seated themselves with a feeling of quiet and security, snugly round their little hearth.

“Shall I go on reading where I left off, gran-gran?” said the pretty child with a smile. The good natured old man nodded assent, at the same time taking out of his portfolio, his lead pencil, paper and ruler, at his accustomed hour, in order to draw designs, which he afterwards exhibited for the instruction of the young artizans, as headmaster of the joiners’ trade.

For the same reason he kept but little company, living quite retired, attended only by a single maid servant, and his little granddaughter.

She had, by this time, seated herself opposite to him, began to turn over the leaves of a huge richly bound folio in parchment, and proceeded to read as follows:

“And it likewise once happened in the famed city of the sea, at Venice, that a gondolier, whose occupation there is to row backwards and forwards in boats, hung with black, upon the canals, had taken into his service a stranger, for his rower, of uncommon size and strength. Neither the gondolier, nor any one else, could learn whence the lusty varlet had last come, nor where was his native place. Some there were, more deeply read, who observing that this huge hireling was deprived of the use of speech, though he could drink well, and hail passengers politely enough, imagined that he must be some great animal metamorphosed through the wondrous power of some sorcerer into the human shape; and that from his strength and docility, he was most likely formed out of an elephant.

“Be that, however, as it may, the gondolier was well satisfied with his journeyman, who, if he devoured a good deal of food, also went through as much labour; and he troubled his head very little with inquiring into his descent and country, leaving all such conjectures to the solution of the learned.

“In this proceeding, however, he could not be justified, as no Christian master and householder ought to engage any servants, whose faith, good character, and conduct are not sufficiently known to him, since he must remain accountable both to God and man for the demeanour of such domestics, or other hired persons.”

Here the old man sighed deeply, and leaned down his head, white with age, upon his hand. Margery stopped and looked at him with surprize. He then recovered himself, and forcing a smile observed, “Well, my love, read on; I want nothing. I was only thinking how much better it had been, if—but go on, Margery, my dear.” And Margery thus proceeded:

“About the same period there happened to pass that way, a famous necromancer, who applied to the said gondolier for three able-bodied boatmen, in order to make a long and quick passage by night. The gondolier thought he was rendering him a great service by letting him have his dumb rower for one of the hands, which he calculated at the rate of five others. This he seemed to shew by the speed with which his gondola began to skim the waves. But just at midnight there was heard, from the vicinity of the route it was then going, a most hideous uproar, in which the voice of the great sorcerer was most loud, and resounded far over the waters. A few of the boldest young men hastened with torches and arms towards the spot. Soon they saw the form of the huge rower conspicuous on the deck, engaged in sinking his own vessel, and stamping it deeper and deeper into the waves below; at the same time he seemed to be playing at ball with the sorcerer, and at a single blow struck off his head, after which boat and boatman both sunk together into the deep.

“On the following morning the shattered limbs of the necromancer were found scattered in different places, washed up by the waves. What appeared still more remarkable was, the discovery of a dead elephant lying, apparently drowned, upon the sea shore, a few miles distant from the city. But whence the strange monster could have been brought, or by what means, no one knew.

“It was surmised, however, by many, that the same necromancer had, by his infernal art, metamorphosed the huge animal into the human form, and employed it in this way, at Venice, for the purpose of effecting some of his diabolical schemes. That at this time he must for once have miscalculated the exact hour and planet under which he was operating; and had unluckily, for himself, been deceived by the evil spirits, with whom he was tampering, so that in ascending the gondola, he did not even recognize the enchanted beast, as oftentimes indeed, happens to such practitioners in the black arts before attaining their end. Others again wished to infer that the magician had only assumed the strange ancient-looking form in which he appeared, and was in reality a very handsome young man, deeply smitten with a passion for the lovely consort of the Doge. That moreover he had sent the huge elephantine rower before him, in order to assist in the abduction of the noble duchess, or at all events to stir up some wild insurrection in the city, and in the state council of the Republic, favourable to his views. As it has been stated, however, he, in this instance, fell a victim to his own want of foresight in directing the potency of his own fatal arts.

“Hence we may learn. . . . .”

Just at these words Margery was interrupted by a tremendous bustle in the street. She cast an anxious glance towards the windows, and at length whispered, “Ah, grandfather; I fear the young gentlemen students are eyen more wild than usual to-day!”

“It is only according to custom,” said the old man with a smile; “and birds of one feather will flock together, as the saying goes. So give no more heed to it, love, than to the blustering of a storm towards spring, and go on quietly with the book.”

Margery was once more applying herself with all diligence to the exact line and word, when suddenly there came three such thundering blows against the window shutters, that the fine old vellum book slipped out of her hand, and she hid her face in the cushion of the arm chair, which rattled, along with all the furniture in the room.

But not so the worthy head master; for hastening close under the window, he exclaimed in the same strong clear tone in which he gave the word of command, when serving à la militaire, in his youth; “Who has the boldness to disturb a free citizen in his own house? Let the wanton young blade give his name from the outside, and we shall soon see if he be as valiant as he would make us believe. As to this house, let him know it is the residence of Head Master Rhenfried—Philibert Rhenfried, President of the Honourable Joiners’ Company, belonging to this town and country. What say ye?”

A low anxious wailing was heard on the outside, very strongly distinguished through all the violent mirth and uproar of the collegians, and gradually dying away along with the same in the distance.

“What was that?” enquired both the grandfather and the child at the same moment, with a look of surprize.

The students meanwhile made a fresh movement, and formed in a grand square in the mark. Torches were seen waving in the air, mingled with no few cudgels: and it is said that a number were observed to be sharpening their hangers upon the stones. Apparently they had pronounced their pereat upon many an unlucky professor’s pate; and in particular upon his, who had so greatly won little Margaret’s regard. For though he was accustomed to banter in a friendly way with some of these wild spirits of the gown, he was extremely bitter and unrelenting, in cases of excessive wickedness and extravagance on their part, inasmuch that between the two, they hardly knew in which way to deal with him. However, they were in hopes, at least, of terrifying him out of the vexatious censorship, which he had assumed, and they were the more emboldened by the efforts of a new collegian, named Marcellin, who had been residing during some weeks, while on a tour, in the town, and ingratiated himself extremely with the whole fraternity by his superior courage and dexterity. Though a good deal older than the usual run of them, he it was who schemed and executed the most mad and juvenile tricks, while at the same time he won equal admiration by his superior abilities and acquirements. He had also conceived a great dislike to poor Margery’s favourite, the Professor Nordenholm; hated to hear him named; could never be prevailed upon to call on him as on the other professors, and felt infinitely delighted at the idea of beholding the rod which was now hanging over him, descend, in terrorem, upon his professional shoulders.

Their whole force marched forthwith until they formed a junction before the said Nordenholm’s house; and there they set up a shout for Marcellin. Marcellin! echoed from a hundred voices, but it was in vain! no Marcellin made his appearance.

At length he was seen sinking quite pale and breathless, with difficulty supporting himself upon his sword-stick, out of the crowd about him. Some of the senior natives approached him with looks of eager and terrific inquiry, while the light of their torches glared strangely upon his livid and distorted features. “What!” cried he, scornfully as they gathered round him, “do you think this either well bred or right to dog me in so scandalous a stile to the very steps of a strange old master joiner, one whom I may not so much as call by name; and would you delude me by maintaining that this is the family house of the hated Professor Nordenholm?”

“Of a truth,” replied one of the students, in no good humoured tone, “the head master resides in Nordenholm’s family house, but who, as you so outrageously insist, has offered to dog your steps thither; and, moreover, how happen you to know any thing respecting Nordenholm’s residence? you who detested to hear him named, and gave yourself no sort of concern about him! all this appears to me somewhat strange.”

Marcellin’s pride took the alarm, but at the word strange, he seemed greatly confused, and replied in a hurried, unconnected manner. This only plunged both parties deeper into the brawl, and shortly, in his excessive choler, he challenged two of the natives to meet him with sword and pistols on the ensuing morning.

After fierce words on both sides, they separated and went in different directions without attempting to resume any of their former schemes, and without a single pereat executed on any professional head.

Nordenholm watched their retreat through his half-closed windows barricadoed with huge tomes, and burst into bitter laughter, as he recalled to mind a similar convulsion, which was years before followed by the loss of his sweetest earthly enjoyments.

Meanwhile the head-master and Margaret had ceased to read, and were sitting nearer each other quite still and contemplative.

“No, read no more to-night, child,” said the old man, “the evening seems to have set in so strangely; and then the history you began to read was so very extraordinary, who knows but still more wild and absurd accounts may follow it; better bring your spinning-wheel to the table, and then if you should happen to call to mind one of your prettiest ditties sing it for me, my dear.”

Margery smiled and nodded her head, at the same time beginning to spin in right earnest, but no pretty song seemed to rise up in her trembling little heart. She seemed rather to anticipate from her looks, though the streets were again quiet, that there was yet something strangely unusual and dismal in the approaching night that weighed heavier and heavier on her mind. Nor were her forebodings felt without reason, for just then they heard heavy footsteps pacing backwards and forwards in the room above them, the same which was occupied by the old lodger who had not yet returned home, and of which he always carried the key about him, being extremely jealous of any one entering it in his absence. At times, too, they thought they heard a fearful sobbing, and sighing, almost like that of a man dying of great pain. Margaret raised up her hands, as if directing her grandfather to the spot, but said not a word, while he went and took down his old broad sword hanging on the wall, then prayed a few moments within himself, and lastly went towards the door.

“Dearest grandfather, my own best grand-papa,” whispered Margaret, “take me with you then! for whatever terrible there may be, it cannot be half so agonizing as I should imagine, were I to be left here in the little study by myself—all alone, with such dreadful thoughts. Oh yes; you must take me along with you!”

And after a few moments, while the old man had been engaged in trimming the lamp for his lanthorn, and putting out the candle which they were before burning, he motioned to the timid girl to accompany him, and lighted her on the way. But she clung fast to him, and they began to ascend the stairs together. As they proceeded up the narrow stone steps, and along the creaking landing, they continued to hear more plainly the same strange moaning and whimpering from the lodger’s chamber. They were now standing before the door, and could perceive there was a light burning within, apparent though the key-hole. “In God’s name,” cried old master Rhenfried, “what kind of being is within there, and in what manner engaged?”

The door flew suddenly open, wide open, and “Huzzah! halloh! who disturbs, who affrights me?” was repeated from a voice within, so horribly wild and mad, that master Rhenfried involuntarily stepped back, and the child fell upon her knees, muttering her prayers behind him.

In the middle of the chamber stood arrayed in a blood-red mantle, the strange lodger, and he trembled greatly. After a short pause, he said in a low hollow voice, “See! take your rent for one half year. It is upon the table; there, take it away, for it fell due the week before.”

“I shall not receive it to-day for all that,” replied the old master, with a firmly recovered and determined tone of voice, “but I both will and must know what it is that so dreadfully agitates you, and by what means you gained access into my fast-locked and bolted dwelling!”

“What I moan, and what I sigh for,” half sobbed and laughed the offended lodger, “Eh! surely the spirits that haunt the gallows have a right to do that; and why not he who regularly and orderly pays for his own lodging? How did I gain access here, you say?—Eh! what kind of questions are these?—why, the house door was standing wide open when I came; upon my honour, I can assure you, nevertheless, that I remarked nothing else.”

“For all that,” said master Rhenfried, “I have earnestly to entreat of you to leave these lodgings to-morrow morning, for truly I am not accustomed to live with people whose doors fly off their hinges when they just approach them; I will never live with them any more.”

“But I do not happen to be of the same opinion,” said the strange lodger, in a contemptuous tone, “I laugh at the idea of going out; you know you are bound over to the former landlord to suffer me to remain, So there is your rent, pick it up, it is all there.”

The old master, glancing sideways at the glittering gold, observed, “Hand to hand; I can receive nothing from you besides; I see you have brought such curious old doubloons, all marked Venice, and Iknow not what date they may bear. I believe too I have said before-time that I am no exchange broker, and have no dealings in strange obsolete coins, though I were to gain ten times the amount by them.”

“Here, however,” cried the lodger, laughing, “are no Venetian doubloons. They are old Saxon gold coins, which your forefathers have been acquainted with these thousand years. And if you sottish folk no longer prize them, yet the former master here, the wonderfully wise Nordenholm, may surely contrive to exchange them. Now pray leave me alone, or take what is due to you!”

And as old master Rhenfried was turning reluctantly away, the strange lodger slammed to the door with such violence as to blow out their light. Slowly and sad did the grandfather and daughter descend the stairs, and along the landing which sounded dismally to their footsteps, until they again reached the snug little study, and felt as if a burden were suddenly removed from their mind. They lighted and trimmed their lamp, and master Rhenfried shouted aloud for the maid-servant, to go instantly with a message for Professor Nordenholm, entreating him to come thither without loss of time. Should he be gone to rest, he must nevertheless get up, and hasten as fast as possible to consider of some very important business.

In a short while the professor made his appearance, pale and terrified. “You have sent for me on account of the lodger—is it not?” he enquired in a low voice: “my God! I might well think how it would be! but let our pretty little Margaret go to bed. Ihave much strange matter for your private ear, and our conference may be prolonged far beyond midnight.”

The head master expressed his assent, and bade the servant go along with Margaret, and both retire to rest. Margery looked a little anxiously round her, but observing that her good old grandfather, as well as the professor, was going to keep watch, she thought it would be better to try and forget her fears in sleep, and, without a word, she bade them both a sweet good night. Soon she fell into a soft slumber, and lost all recollection of the fearful occurrences of that dismal night: it had no longer power over her gentle spirit, for the smile that played upon her lips betokened innocent and angelic rest.

Meanwhile the professor and master Rhenfried were in earnest communion together, seated near one another at the little round table. After a long pause, the former in a low and fearful tone thus resumed the discourse: “I ought in the outset, my dear Rhenfried, to remind you of a great calamity which happened to you, though I am also aware, that so singular a period of your excellent life, should, if possible, be wrapped in an impenetrable veil of oblivion; but it is all of no use now. I loved your lost daughter who disappeared ten years ago, and if she did not return my affection, there was a time when she seemed to receive it with a degree of sweet complacency and friendship. The cause of the beloved girl’s loss, so inexpressibly bitter to my feelings, remains still as unaccountable to me as I suppose it yet does to you.”

The old man made a sign for him to say no more, and seemed to be absorbed in deep meditation within himself. At length he said, “No! that dreadful occurrence is not such a complete mystery as you seem to think, though more severely felt, my dear sir, than any similar affliction that perhaps ever befell me. Yet, when I take all into consideration—your known integrity; your present sincerity; your kind attachment to my grand-daughter, and the confidence she seems to feel in you; I feel I can no longer withhold mine; I feel that you fully merit it, and I will state every circumstance I know relating to the fate of my poor unfortunate girl.

“It may now be rather more than twelve years ago when there came to my house, where till then I had resided so quietly and pleasantly with my little girls;—there came, I say, one day, a handsome young man who expressed a wish to see my workshop, and after examining my models, &c. very attentively, he began to talk about an apprenticeship. As you may imagine, I at first treated the matter as mere jest, and then rejected it as a piece of uncalled for mockery on his part, warmly entreating him not to think of amusing himself at my expense. Still the young gentleman insisted he intended neither jest nor insult; he was much attached to turning and joiners’ work of all kinds, and he had resolved to become acquainted with it in all its branches thoroughly, and upon principle, under the care and instructions of a skilful master. He then hoped he had succeeded, and he was resolved, with my permission, never to relinquish his design, until he had made himself fairly master of all that it was in my power to teach. Like a madman, as I was, I gave my consent, though I knew literally nothing either who he was, or whence he came; not even whether he had any testimonials with him. I shewed him every thing in my-shop; drew up an agreement, as if the devil possessed me, and called him at his own request, by the name of Ludibert Wendelstern.”

“Ludibert!” said Nordenholm mournfully,—“Alas; there is a Ludibert occurs, likewise, in my own history. But go on! go on! Dear master. Was he then, the man who deprived you of your angelic daughter?”

“He! he! no other on earth!” replied the old man; his face growing darker and darker as he spoke. “Right well did the cunning seducer know how to apply himself to my noble art; never had I an apprentice half so skilful, for he possessed fine talents, and in more branches than one. He could play the flute beautifully, and could sing as well; while with his rapier he was a perfect master.”

Nordenholm earnestly signified his assent, and the old man continued, without noticing it.

“During our leisure hours he amused himself with instructing the rest of the apprentices and their companions in the noble science of defence, and having myself been a soldier, fond of the sword exercise, it afforded me no slight pleasure to witness their feats with the foil. On all occasions the young master exhibited the greatest politeness and good breeding in his conduct, and daily established himself more firmly in my good graces. This continued for the space of two years; when suddenly the scales fell from my deluded eyes, and I stood lost in astonishment and dismay. The young students had engaged in a similar piece of work to that we have witnessed this evening; and one of those who returned no more that night to supper, and was never afterwards seen, was Ludibert Wendelstern. On the ensuing morning I found a paper lying in my daughter Agnes’ chamber, but she was gone—gone for ever.”

The old man here rose, and unlocking a small cupboard, took out two letters which he handed to the Professor, who recognizing the hand of his beloved Agnes, began to read, though almost blinded by the tears that came into his eyes.

“A happy destiny calls me away from you, my dear father; but I know you would never have yielded me your consent. Farewell, then, and take comfort; for I feel quite assured we shall soon meet again, when you will congratulate me a thousand, thousand times on the happiness which will soon be mine.”

“That,” said the old master, “was indeed a poor prophecy,” and he drew his hand across his eyes, as if in pain: “she was far too confident, and that ever brings failure and disappointment along with it, for wretched mortals such as we are. There is only one thing certain, but that is quite certain; wherefore the Lord be praised.”

He took his cap from his reverend white head, held it between his folded hands, and prayed within himself. Afterwards he continued, with more cheerful resignation:—“During four years I could learn nothing regarding her; but at the expiration of that period, one fine morning, an infant of about four years old was found wrapped delicately up, and laid at my door. It was Margaret, and the following note was found attached to its arm; which I will endeavour to read to you:

“I have been lawfully united at the altar with my beloved Ludibert; and the sweet pledge of our affection which I herewith commit to your care, was, I assure you, by all that is holy, born in honorable wedlock. If you would not wish to curse, and to kill me, I beseech you to preserve the dear infant for me, until I come to claim her; till when her existence must remain a mystery. My noble consort maintains me in great wealth and splendor; yet, oh, best and dearest father, you cannot believe what abundance of wishful tears I shed—what sighs I pour, once more to cross our sweet home’s threshold; and which I am fondly trusting soon to do. Oh, think often of your absent, but faithful, fondly-loving,

“Agnes.”

“In the basket that contained the child was a large sum of gold and silver, with precious stones. This, however, I deposited as the subscription of some stranger for the use of St. Ursula’s hospital. But I deliberated not a moment in announcing that the young child was my grand-daughter, the offspring of the marriage of my daughter with the stranger. And now, God be praised, our good city is pleased to give full credit to any assertion from the lips of head-master Philibert Rhenfried: so far my good name helped me, and I troubled myself no farther with any needless inquiries. So at all events, my poor Agnes has not been the occasion of adding the sin of lying to the account of her aged father’s soul. I have brought up her little girl to the best of my knowledge of what is good and right, and so by Heaven’s mercy she has gone on improving, doubtless under its wise dispensations, to the fulfilment of God’s purposes here below.”

Nordenholm here pressed the old man’s hand; and leaning down his head, wept bitterly. After a long sad pause he then said: “Alas, my good master, I see how much you suffer, but your sufferings are not barbed with the stings of guilt; therefore do you bear them freely and boldly. But woe alas! I feel no sweet confidence in the same freedom. I have my misgivings, though I have nothing dreadful to reproach myself with. There is something weighs at my heart, which seems to grow heavier and heavier as the night proceeds.

“The cause of this first arose on occasion of the fore-mentioned festival, when I was young and happy, alas, doubly happy, for I then flattered myself with delightful hopes of winning your daughter’s love;—and came along with other students to enjoy ourselves here.

“After our rounds, we held jubilee in a grand decorated hall, where we were joined by a mask arrayed in yery splendid apparel. We had once, and only once, before observed the same man make his appearance, and concluded that he was one of our merry company who had some especial piece of mirth in view. This time the unknown made his obeisance, and with very humble yoice, petitioned for leave to propose a question for the consideration of our society. Receiving our unanimous consent, he began;—‘It is a question of honor and of duty;—whether a lover have a right to carry off his beloved when he is persuaded that he can maintain her in all due and lawful honor and worthiness; and is equally persuaded that her happiness and his own can be accomplished by no other means.’ He paused; and the voices on both sides rose loud on the ear; though most were perceptibly in favor of a mad assent to such a proposition; many of the students being pretty well heated with wine, and full of adventurous spirit, eager for exploits. I, even I! good master; joined in the wild and wicked votes that carried the question; but it was the first truly blameable act of my life. Even now within this last half hour, I have heard from your own lips, how very lamentably I may have assisted, by such a vote, by supporting such a proposal, in striking at my own sweetest hopes of happiness on earth.”

He hid his face in his hands, and was silent. The old master laid his hand gently upon his bowed head, and while he pronounced his forgiveness, also gave his blessing: his repentance was enough. Nordenholm then rose with renewed hope and strength, and thus continued:

“It seemed, at the same moment, as if I was carried away by a strange impulse of wilful rioting and folly, quite foreign to my usual calm and moderate feelings of enjoyment on such occasions. It appeared as if I no longer recognized myself; I wished to be foremost in the mad career we were pursuing, every where ambitious to give a spur to the follies of the hour; and in all companies striving to lead the revels, in singing, dancing, drinking or rioting. Shortly I heard reports that the stranger was exerting himself very strenuously among our colleagues to obtain some of the most bold and adventurous hands for the purpose of carrying into effect the identical exploit which had gained our unanimous applause; and that he spared no powers of oratory, no influence, to gain his point. My rude and boisterous mirth seemed to offend his more genteel and delicate bearing; and soon we had words together. Then he tore the mask from his face, and we beheld a perfectly strange, but beautiful youth, with a smile of scorn upon his features, which could not, however, impair their noble symmetry and lively expression. ‘My name is Ludibert;’ he cried, approaching me nearer, ‘for that of my family, it is noble, princely; but I shall not mention it to you. Enough that I now cite you to appear and decide our difference in honorable combat: enough that I so far condescend.’

“The challenge was as quickly received; every thing was prepared; I met him with perfect ease and confidence; for I was the unrivalled master of our ring, and stripped to our shirts, with single rapiers, we set to. Almost at the first pass, I was overpowered by the irresistible vigor of my rival’s arm: I could not even stand my guard; but was instantly struck senseless and bleeding to the ground; a part of his weapon sticking in my breast.

“Many weeks afterwards, on my first return of consciousness, my first inquiries were respecting Agnes, and the tale of her abduction then saluted my ears. I could learn nothing of the time and place, while my ideas on the subject were so mingled with the occurrences of that dreadful night, that I could only feel remorse for the mad disposition which I had indulged, and confess myself unworthy of the happiness which once appeared in store for me.

“Yet alas, good sir, my cup was not yet full. There was a favorite subject, I don’t much like to mention, which I once pursued for the sake of poetical embellishment—the research after strange old charms, and other magical influences; and this, my despair respecting the fate of Agnes, now led me to employ, for the purpose of discovering whither the beloved girl had disappeared. Ah, my worthy master; fix not your eye so sternly, so reproachfully upon me, much less turn away your sympathy from my sorrows; for know, God be praised, I have never either denied or misapplied what is holy by any instigation or pursuit of mine.” At the same time he stretched out his right hand in token of such assurance, which the good master with a look of compassion accepted and motioned to him to proceed; as he did in the following words:—

“I knew that it has been conceived possible through a fit conjunction of times and circumstances, so to fabricate a magical mirror, that it shall retain the moon’s beams in such a manner, as to exhibit by secret reflexion on the surface, every thing that passes upon the earth’s sphere in succession, according as such magic mirror shall be directed and applied. This wonderful piece of mechanism I succeeded with infinite labour and great expence in procuring; and once in the garden of this your, but formerly my house, I began, when the moon was shining clear in the heavens, and at the full, about the eleventh hour of night, to try my secret experiment. That my own apparition would be seen, in case my image fell upon my glass; seen even from the farthest corner of the earth, I was well aware; but my whole soul was so intent upon learning the fate and residence of Agnes, that I could dwell upon nothing else.

“It now seemed as if some assistant being were directing my hand in the motions of the mirror, which fortunately had been placed aright. At first only small strange forms cast their reflexions over the surface of the mirror; when at length, in the direction of the south, there arose one so enchantingly sweet and lovely before my eyes!—Oh my good master! father! she sat looking so beautiful and angelic, amidst the blooming orange bowers, in the soft moonlight which shed its beams upon the lofty pines that crowned the heights above——”

“I see your eyes sparkle with delight;” interrupted the old man, in a tone of displeasure; “you ought rather to take shame and sorrow to yourself, for having dared to dabble in any forbidden species of witchcraft, than to display the least feeling of exultation. Let me hear you describe what follows, with a becoming degree of seriousness and regret;—what farther appeared?”

With the humility of a repentant offender, the Professor cast his eyes upon the ground, and in a lower tone said, “It was, indeed, Agnes! she was splendidly attired, and was again seen walking by moonlight leaning on Ludibert’s arm. I concealed my features cautiously, at a distance, to prevent them from falling upon the mirror. Next, you yourself, Sir, suddenly appeared in the garden; and on the mirror’s surface the pale and sorrowful cast of your features was plainly visible. Seized with alarm, lest you too should catch sight of Agnes, I ran to the glass, beheld my own distorted features reflected there; and bursting into a thousand fragments the wonderful instrument fell from my trembling grasp.”

“I know it all, as well as if it happened to day,” said the white-headed Rhenfried; “yet amidst all the images that floated before my eyes I could distinguish no one; clouds of heart-sprung tears concealed them from view. For at that time I had not fully resigned myself to the will of God: I lay weeping upon my bed, but suddenly I heard a light whispering as if it had said in my ear, ‘Rise, unhappy father; in Nordenholm’s house it is known what is become of thy daughter.’ I obeyed, and doubtless it was no good spirit, which had so whispered me in my chamber. Then when I came and found you labouring under such excessive terror, you know well that I retired without speaking a single word, and never more alluded to the appalling and mysterious subject. Long afterwards, however, a heavy weight seemed to oppress my soul; from which you may learn, my poor deluded friend, how very critical and dangerous a pursuit it is, that can involve in its forbidden operations even the peace of the innocent, who would willingly resist its incantations to their last breath.”

Meanwhile they again began to hear the voice of the strange lodger above stairs, mingled with sobs and sighs, and wild fierce laughter, even louder than before.

“Good God!” cried the Professor in much alarm;—“suppose the horrid noises were to awaken the child!” Already he had raised his hand with threatening gesture towards the room above; when instantly checking himself, he sank down upon his knees and said: “Help! help me to pray! good master; that will avail us much better here.” Both then prayed, and all grew still!

When they had again seated themselves at the table, the old master first spoke:

“Assuredly, Mr. Professor, you must have disturbed my mind by some other means, besides those used with the magical mirror. You had better at once speak boldly out, and confess how it is that this strange unhappy lodger continues here; he is in some way connected with your proceedings.”

“So indeed it is,” replied Nordenholm. “For having learned that my Agnes was to be sought for somewhere in the south, I instantly collected the scattered remnants of my fortune, in order to seek her in those parts. The better to further my views, and gain access to various classes of society I assumed the title of Doctor and Professor. While I was absent, you were presented with little Margaret whom you found at your own door, but it was my fate alas, to encounter many less fair and pleasing sights, cruel and frightful adventures, which bore me, like a whirlpool, into the gulf.

“I had journeyed as far as the city of Venice. There I heard mention of a certain sorcerer, who knew how to unravel all mysteries upon earth, and as I found all my inquiries after my lost Agnes were fruitless, I formed an acquaintance with him; and he is the very same strange being, whom we just now heard crying out and lamenting over our head. On consulting him he declared that he must have some fixed abode, where he might prepare his conjurations, and that having first provided him with a floor in my own house, he would attend to my wishes. When he got possession, however, he did not keep his word; pretending that the image of Agnes appeared only dimly floating before his eyes. Moreover, I heard it currently reported at Venice that this was merely the apparition of a real sorcerer, who had flourished centuries ago, and owing to some want of foresight in his art had fallen a sudden victim; and never since been enabled to enjoy the least repose.”

“Just Heavens! that I feared,” exclaimed Rhenfried. “Margaret has this very evening read me his dreadful history aloud! Come what may, however, no time is to be lost; we must rid the house of him, at all events.” As he had said this, the old master proceeded once more to trim his lanthorn; took his good sword under his arm, and strode boldly out of the room. Nordenholm ventured not to oppose him, but followed at a distance trembling with doubt and terror, up the steps and along the sounding staircase until they reached the strange lodger’s room.

The grey-headed host knocked smartly at the door; it began to open very slowly, but not as if moved by a human hand; for the fearful guest was seated quite at the other end of the chamber, upon the ground, wrapped in a red mantle; several household implements scattered round him, and a dull blue fire flickering and casting its fitful shadows upon the opposite walls.

The strange lodger cast a keen glance at the intruders, with a smile of scorn upon his lips; and as they continued to gaze upon him, more fierce and fiery glances shot from his hollow eyes.

“Give yourselves no trouble;” he shouted in a hollow voice; “I well know your object, and what you want here; but nothing will come of it, at least during your lives; and it is a question even whether Master Philibert’s grand-children will make me quit. For I am of a very tenacious nature, and apt to tarry long at a place.”

The Professor here sighed deeply from the bottom of his soul. The Red Mantle tried to force a laugh, but in this he could not rightly succeed; though he said in triumph; “One of you, I well know, is burdened with heavy thoughts. Of that at least I am certain!”

“For me,” replied old master Philibert, very calmly,—“for me, I feel still more certain that I am not the person. Yea! and I know something yet more; that you will not yenture to stay in this house another quarter of an hour; for I hereby conjure you, in pure and lively faith, with the fear of God before my eyes, confiding in him only, to depart from hence out of this house, and never to cross its threshold more. What is more, you shall decamp forthwith, secretly and quietly, without offering to disturb a single Christian soul within these walls, without any knocking, rumbling, or roaring of any kind. Now!—avaunt!—are you going? or will you have me appeal to more strong and terrible adjurations, in the name of the Lord. Will you wait, and rue your folly, or be gone?” At these last words, with quick, horrible and threatening gestures, the lodger gathered up his strange furniture and hiding them under his red mantle, he hastened towards the door, fiercely murmuring as he went by, “Thou cunning old Professor—thou arch deceiver—not a word in my defence, against that savage greybeard; dumb villain as thou art! I will away from these walls—but then what woe—what woe—yet—yet.”

His voice continued to utter this, close in their ears, after he himself had disappeared. With the careful eye of a prudent householder and father, master Rhenfried, examined all parts of the room with his lanthorn, in order to ascertain that nothing of an unhallowed or diabolical kind had been left in the haunted room. He could discover nothing, except that upon the little table there remained the same old gold coins, counted out in payment of the strange lodger’s rent.

“Hem!” said the master, thinking awhile to himself, “an honest ghost in his way; yet I must not venture to take possession of it; though, again it is doubtless a God-send, which ought not to be buried without turning to use, nor misapplied;—I will conyey it then to St. Ursula’s Hospital. Morning is already glimmering through the window-shutters; I think we will awaken little Margaret, and take her along with us, for the child is always eager, and even quite fond of walking that way; none so pleasant, she thinks, when I go along with her.”

Very soon, then, the Professor and master Rhenfried were proceeding on their route, conducting the pretty Margery carefully between them, along the beautiful avenue of lime trees which leads with gentle ascent to the front of the Hospital. The little girl laughed and jested in so artless and engaging a manner, as to lighten up the sad contemplative features of her companions with occasional smiles. They met one of the women of the establishment, and clasping her little hands, Margery addressed her in the most friendly voice:—“Ah, lady Sibyl! ah, lady Sibyl! thou that art wont to bring me always such sweet fruit, and get’st nothing but a pat on the cheek in return. Good morning, a very good morning, lady Sibyl.”

Just at that moment was heard a confused uproar on the opposite side to where they stood, and a group of students made their appearance carrying a bier, apparently with some wounded person, to seek assistance at the hospital. Lady Sibylla, at this sight, breaking loose from the child, hastened to her post; the two friends followed her thoughtfully, while Margery hid herself anxiously behind a rose bush.

The bier was now laid down, the students gathered round in a circle, while the woman began cautiously to examine the person’s wounds. They all made way, however, for the Professor and Master Rhenfried with marks of great respect, and one of them began to whisper them how the strange student, Marcellin, had engaged with and disarmed one of the senior students, and then confessed the injustice of which he had been guilty on the previous evening, upon which a complete reconciliation took place. “So it might have been, likewise, with the second duel,” continued the relater, “or at least nothing fatal would perhaps have happened; when suddenly—no one knew whence—an old strange looking man clad in a red mantle stood in the midst of us all, murmuring some unintelligible words, and looking highly displeased at us. The combatants seemed to fight more and more furiously. In a moment the stranger stooping down, filled his hands with sand which he cast repeatedly with the speed of light in thick clouds between the rivals, at the same time loudly laughing, ‘Hail to you, old master! well a day! have I played you a trick? now for Venice; now thou hast got it well—woe—woe!’

“We heard him say these words, though he was gone, nobody seemed to know how. Lost in astonishment, we at length turned our eyes to the duellists who both lay bleeding upon the ground; the senior was dead, and Marcellin we have here brought along with us in the situation you see. Their seconds have made their escape: and we, though less guilty, are come forward willingly to deliver ourselves up to whatever punishment may be thought due. No, we did not leave him helpless upon the ground.”

The Professor and Rhenfried, not without evident reluctance and shuddering, drew nigh the bier; pale and bloody, Marcellin raised himself up; he knew Nordenholm; moaned, and then exclaimed in rage, “Thou black sorcerer—abandoned sorcerer—I swore to do it—I saw thy hateful visage when you conjured up the image of my sweet wife’s father, all sorrowful and bathed in tears. Then sat she in her orange bower, near Naples—in the soft moonshine—know you it—know you it well? In an agony of remorse she turned away from me, and thenceforth our bonds of love were broken asunder ... Nay, I have never since once beheld her any where on this wide and desolate earth. Then hastened I hither, to have my revenge on thee: and here I must sadly die. And yet now were all obstacles overcome; and the sweet saint were again mine—the partner of my ducal power and splendour—she, for whose sake I became a vile apprentice—and God knows what worse—yea, I had led her home—had her mine own in all the pride of love and splendour ... But now she is far away, and I am dying—dying, another and another victim of thy hateful infernal arts.”

A murmur was heard among the students, “The fever is mounting into his head;” others, however, were more doubtful, and hazarded a variety of conflicting conjectures. Master Rhenfried looked round him with a free and friendly air; he then took his cap off his fine grey head, and spoke in a clear but mild tone, “To the very respectable young students, and any other spectators who may wish to put questions on this affair, I here stake my life and honor, that professor Nordenholm is wholly innocent of causing this young man’s death.”

The murmurs became still, all moved respectfully in token of assent to the worthy old man, and they began to advance excuses, and canvass the professor’s conduct in a more favourable manner. He himself, however, appeared unconscious of what was passing around him, he stood the very picture of grief, the hot bitter tears coursing each other down his cheeks.

Master Rhenfried meanwhile bent over the dying man, and with gentle firmness said, “You will soon appear in the presence of the great God, my dear sir, and now you see before you the face of that man whom you have the most deeply betrayed and injured, even deprived of his last sweetest hopes on earth. But God be praised—I know, I confess, Him who purchased us with his blood; bore all our sins, and has paid the price even for yours. So take comfort, dear sir, I forgive you from the bottom of my soul, and if you depart with feelings of reconciliation and regret, be assured you will likewise meet with still greater compassion—pardon—blessed peace, in that better state to which you are now fast hastening. With whatever evil, deceit, and falsehood, Ludibert, you so vilely assumed the name of Wendelstern on earth, I do confidently predict that for this your sorrow and ruth, you shall yet retain your name, and become a fair bright star (stern) in Heaven, high above all your earthly pomp and state; in a sphere where friend and enemy may unite in the enjoyment of the same heavenly blessedness and delights. Go, take thy rest then, dear Ludibert, with a meek and reconciled spirit, in holy hope, in lively assurance, that thou shalt wake ’mid the light of a brighter and happier morn.”

The supposed Marcellin, now the unhappy Ludibert, stretched forth his hands to the good master, and mildly turning his eyes to the spot where stood the late hated Nordenholm, a friendly smile played upon his features; he pressed his hand, bowed down his head upon it, and died.

Now, too, it was first observed, that the female attendant had fallen into a swoon by the side of the bier. The old man gently raised up her head, and held her until she came to herself; when, refusing all farther assistance, with feeble step, and drawing her hood and cloak closer around her, she proceeded towards the hospital. The students again raised the bier, and in perfect silence bore the deceased slowly along towards an ancient half-dilapidated church at a short distance; while Nordenholm not a little consoled after seeing Ludibert’s happy departure, with his usual promptness and decision pointed out to them, in few words, when they had laid down the bier at the church door, all that was necessary to be observed on such an occasion, and how they might best clear up their conduct by shunning not, and by disguising nothing from the civil power.

The students bowing respectfully and returning their unanimous thanks, while they at the same time condoled with him, then took their leave, shewing by the sorrow of their countenances, how much their hearts were amended.

Meanwhile the spital woman had beckoned the aged Rhenfried to accompany her, and stopped as she was entering the hospital under the vaulted entrance, where she began to enter into earnest discourse with him. Seeing the professor approaching, the old master beckoned to him, and said, “Here, friend, this good woman wishes to communicate something to us; let us hear her!”

She then threw back her veil and hood, and there stood before them the long-lost and lamented Agnes; saintly pale, indeed, and bearing the traces of deep suffering, but whose features were not to be mistaken by the eye of a father, and of a lover. In the same serious and lofty frame of mind, produced by what had so recently happened, all three seemed now to regard earthly sorrows and earthly wishes with a spirit of serene and cheerful patience, and whatever the future might have in store for them, either to part with or bear, they were already prepared for, and saw as it were approaching along the vista of coming years.

Little Margaret who had laid herself to sleep beside the rose tree, overpowered with the last night’s anxieties and fatigue, now came skipping towards them, and playfully caressing the weeping Agnes, said, “How beautiful you look this morning, dear lady Sibylla, now you have thrown aside your black cap and hood, but you must not cry—women never cry!” But her delight knew no bounds when she learned that the lady was going home to live with her, and was to have the room of the strange old lodger for her own, who was never coming back any more.

This, too, she found to be all true; she was quite enraptured at the change, and under the delicate and incessant guardianship and attentions lavished upon her by the three friends, pretty Margery grew and flourished, until she bloomed in full beauty, one of the most fair and lovely flowers in the rich garland of Germany’s gentle women.

It was a lovely Italian evening, when a young German merchant, named Richard, entered Venice, the widely celebrated seat of traffic and commerce. In consequence of it being then the period of the thirty years war, all Germany was, at that time, a scene of dissension; no wonder, therefore, if the young merchant, who was a gallant more inclined to banqueting and luxurious indulgence, than feats of chivalry, was not greatly displeased at his affairs calling him for some time towards Italy, where things wore a less hostile appearance, and where too, he had heard, that there was no lack either of the richest wines, or the most delicious fruits—to say nothing of fascinating beauties, in which latter article our gallant piqued himself on being no ordinary connoisseur.

Seated in his gondola, he traversed the various canals of the city, struck with admiration at the beautiful buildings, and still more so at the lovely tenants, whom he frequently beheld, peeping from their lattices. At length he arrived at a magnificent mansion, at whose windows, he saw some ten or twelve charming girls.

“Now, would to heaven,” exclaimed the captivated gallant, “that I had but the opportunity of saying a few words to one of those rare creatures!”

“Well!” returned his gondolier “an that be all, you have only to step out, and go boldly into the house at once:—your time, I warrant me, will pass pleasantly enough.”

“It may be pleasant enough, friend, to thee, to put thy jeers upon strangers; but dost thou suppose that I am such an arrant loon as to follow thy knavish counsel, and to venture where I should not only be hooted out, but receive too a sound drubbing, into the bargain?”

“My good master,” replied the other, “do not think to teach me the customs of our city; only follow my advice, and, if you are not welcomed with open arms,—why then I am well content to lose my labour and my fare.”

The youth now began to think the experiment worth trying; and soon found that the Gondolier had not imposed upon him. These beauties, he quickly discovered, were far from being prudish or tyrannical; on the contrary, they were of that courteous sort, who are never backward in shewing hospitality to the stranger, but ready to extend their complaisance to the utmost, for the triffling consideration of some fifty ducats. “This same Italy,” thought the unwary spark, intoxicated by their voluptuous caresses, “is assuredly the most delightful place beneath heaven;” for he did not fail to impute the flattering reception he had experienced, in no small degree to the comely person, with which nature had favoured him. The demand, however, that was made upon his purse, soon dissipated some of these pleasing reflections, as he discovered, that instead of having made a conquest of some princess, he had only been entertained by a courtisan, who now made a demand that nearly drained his purse. Yet did he not lose all his patience, since he was a gallant that did not consider the cost bestowed upon his pleasures, flung away: he therefore retired with as good a grace, as he could muster on such an occasion, and repaired to a tavern for the sake of diverting his spleen.

Having commenced his affairs in so notable a manner, the wild spark continued daily to indulge in revels, and in the society of mirthful faces. In all the company of brave gallants, with whom Richard now constantly associated, there was but one countenance overcast with gloom. It was that of a Spanish captain, who, though he never failed to be present at these scenes of riot, rarely bestowed a word upon the company, while his dark features were rendered still more gloomy, by the visible uneasiness that sat upon them. Still his presence was endured, as he was a man of rank and wealth, and one too who regarded lightly the expence of treating his friends evening after evening.

Richard, in the mean while, although less liberal of his purse than on the first evening of his arrival at Venice, found his finances rapidly decreasing; and reflected with no small sorrow, that this gay and joyous kind of life, must quickly terminate. His associates were not slow in observing his melancholy, or in devining the cause of it,—this being, by no means, the first instance of the kind, that had occured within their society,—neither did they spare their taunts upon the occasion, so that our gallant was fain to venture among them the last precious relics of his purse. At this prosperous period of his history, the Spaniard called him, one evening, aside and, with unexpected courtesy, requesting that he would accompany him abroad, conducted him to a lone and retired spot. The poor youth was, at first, rather alarmed; but, at length, somewhat quieted his apprehensions by reflecting, that his companion well knew; that he had little about him worth aught, save his skin, and in that he was determined a hole should not be picked without returning the compliment.

The Spaniard, however, having first seated himself on the ruins of an old building, and compelled his companion to do the same, addressed him as follows:

“I cannot help imagining, my dear young friend, that you stand greatly in need of that which has long become a burthen to myself—namely, the power of procuring whatever sum of money you choose, and whenever you please. This power, such as it is, I am willing to dispose of to you for a triffling consideration, besides some other advantages into the bargain.”

“What occasion,” enquired Richard, “can you possibly have for money, if you wish to part with the power of obtaining it yourself?”

“The case stands thus,” returned the captain, “I know not, whether you are acquainted with certain little spirits, that are called bottle-imps; they are small black devils, inclosed in a little phial. Whoever possesses one of these, can command from it whatever worldly possession he desires most, especially abundance of gold. In return for these services, the soul of the person who possesses the imp becomes forfeit to Lucifer, in case he die without having previously disposed of him. But this can be done only by receiving a less sum than that which he first paid for the spirit. Mine cost me ten ducats:—for nine it is yours.”

While the youth was reflecting on this extraordinary offer, the Spaniard continued, “I could, if I pleased, easily get rid of the thing, by palming it upon some one as a mere curiosity, in which manner a knavish fellow inveigled me to purchase it. But I wish not to have the weight of such an ill-deed upon my conscience, and therefore, very honestly and fairly, acquaint you with the bargain. You are still young and high-spirited, and will not fail to meet with opportunities enough of disposing of your purchase, whenever you may become as weary of, as I am even now.”

“My noble Sir,” replied Richard, “an you would not take it ill at my hands, so could I inform you, how often I have been imposed upon already, in this good city of Venice.”

“Why thou foolish varlet,” exclaimed the enraged Spaniard, “thou needest but call to mind the brave entertainment I gave last evening, to judge whether I would cheat thee for the sake of a paltry nine ducats!”

“Who spends much, wants much:” gently observed the young merchant, “and the longest purse we know has a bottom, although not a golden one. If, therefore, you yesterday spent your last ducat, to-day you may be hankering after mine.”

“Excuse me if I do not chastise thee with a cold steel for this insolence:—that I do not do it, is because I still hope that you will help to rid me of my bottle-devil. Besides it is my intention to perform penance, which would only be rendered still heavier thereby.”

“Might we not, at least be favoured with some specimen of the thing’s abilities?” enquired the wary merchant.

“How may that be?” answered the other. “It will neither remain with any one, nor aid any one, save him who has fairly purchased and paid for it.”

The youth could not help feeling some alarm, for the place where they were sitting, seemed a particularly lone and gloomy spot,—although the Spaniard assured him, that he would not employ compulsive means. Yet, in spite of his fears, his imagination dwelt upon the enjoyments that would be in his power, should he become possessor of the little spirit; he determined, therefore, to try whether he could obtain the bargain at a cheaper rate.

“Witless fellow that thou art,” exclaimed the Spaniard with a laugh, “it is for thy sake, and for the sake of those who shall come after thee, that I demand the highest sum I can, that I may delay, as long as possible, the time when it shall be purchased for the smallest coin possible, and the purchaser thereby become inevitably forfeit to the devil, even because he cannot sell it again at a lower price.”

“Well” said Richard, with a tone of delight, “let me but have it. I warrant me I shall not be very eager to get quit of my purchase in a hurry. If, therefore, I could have it for five ducats——”

“It is all one to me,” returned the Spaniard, “but remember you are hastening on the minute when the evil spirit shall claim the last unhappy possessor as his own.”

With these words he delivered up to his companion, in return for his gold, a small glass phial, wherein Richard could just discern, by the light of the stars, something dark that kept leaping up and down.

By way of making an experiment he demanded, although but mentally, to have double the amount of the sum he had just expended, in his right hand, when he instantly felt ten ducats there. He now returned in glee to the tavern, and the rest of the company, who were still carousing there, were not a little astonished at perceiving what cheerful countenances were now worn by those, who were lately in so melancholy a mood. But the Spaniard quickly retired without awaiting the costly banquet which, late as it was, Richard had ordered to be prepared, having first satisfied the demands of the wary host before hand, for his pockets were now well lined with brave new ducats, which flocked thither merely at his wishing.

Those who are most anxious for a similar bargain, will best imagine what kind of a life our wild gallant now led:—unless, indeed, they should be devoted to mere sordid avarice. Even the most charitable, may well suppose that he spent not his days or nights in abstinence and fasting. The first thing he did was to choose, as the minion of his pleasures, the courtisan whose acquaintance cost him so dear at his first arrival at Venice. On this worthless creature did he lavish unheard of sums, purchasing for her a mansion in the city, and two villas, all of which he furnished with the utmost sumptuousness.

It chanced one day, as he was sitting with Lucretia, such was the name of his harlot mistress, in the garden of one of his villas, upon the bank of a little stream, that she suddenly snatched the phial which Richard constantly wore in his bosom, attached to his neck by a chain of gold. She had seized it before he was aware, and now held the little bottle up against the light. At first she was highly amused at beholding the antics of the little black figure; but at length shrieked out in a voice of terror:—“Ah! the nasty creature is a toad!” and immediately flung chain, phial, and bottle-devil, altogether into the water, where the current as quickly carried them away.

The youth endeavoured, as well as he could, to conceal his distress, lest his mistress should enquire farther into the matter, and perhaps accuse him publicly of witchcraft. He pretended therefore, that it was merely a curious toy; then, as soon as he could, he quitted Lucretia, in order to consider what was best for him now to do. He was still in possession of his palace and villas, and had, moreover in his pockets, no inconsiderable sum, in the shape of bright ducats. But how great was his joy when, on putting his hand into his pocket to examine the latter, he discovered there his lost phial. The chain probably remained at the bottom of the stream, but the phial and its little black tenant had faithfully returned back to their owner.—“Now then,” exclaimed he, in a burst of transport, “now then, I find that I possess here a treasure, of which no accident, no earthly power can possibly deprive me!” Nay, he had even kissed the very phial, had not the little jumping black figure excited his aversion, so loathsome did it appear.

If his doings were wild and mad enough before, they were now ten times worse. The infatuated youth regarded even the potentates and princes of the world with a disdainful compassion; convinced that not one of them was able to indulge in such a luxurious life as himself. Even Venice, the most opulent mart in the world, could hardly find dainties enough for his extravagant banquets. Did a well meaning friend hint at the imprudence of this continual rioting, he would indignantly reply: “Richard is my name, and my riches are boundless.” Often, would he, in a fit of intemperate mirth, rudely jest at the folly of the Spaniard, who had cast such a prize from him, and, as he had heard it reported, had retired into a convent.

On this earth, however, there is nothing that lasts for ever. This too our gallant soon experienced to be truth, much sooner, indeed, than he would otherwise have done, in consequence of the intemperance with which he plunged into all sensual delights. A languor like that of death seized his exhausted frame, in spite of all the virtue of his phial, which he vainly kept invoking for health, at the first attack of his disease. Recovery visited him not, but on the contrary frightful dreams.

It seemed to him that one of the phials which were standing by his bed-side, began to set up a wild dance, jostling against the rest in a furious manner. After gazing at it for some minutes, Richard recognized it to be that in which the little spirit was inclosed, and exclaimed: “Bottle-devil, bottle-devil, thou assistest me no more, but rather destroyest that which should work my cure.” Whereupon the little black thing sang in a hoarse voice:

Richard! Richard! prayest in vain:
Prepare thee now for eternal pain;
Therein must thou abide and endure,
Since spirit’s power can work no cure.
No herb that groweth, death can heal:—
I joy, for that thou’rt mine I feel.”

After which it immediately stretched itself out, quite long and thin, and, notwithstanding that Richard held the phial stopped as closely as possible, it crept out between his thumb and the cork: it then suddenly became a large black man, who began to dance in the most hideous manner, clapping to and fro, at the same time, his huge dusky wings; and at length placed his hairy, leathern breast upon Richard’s bosom, and his grinning face upon Richard’s face, so that the latter felt as if he were himself assuming the hideous figure, and in tone of wild agony screamed out for a mirror.

A cold sweat stood upon his brow, as he awoke out of the ghastly dream, and he thought that he perceived a monstrous black toad creep down beside him into his bed; but, upon putting down his hand, he felt only the phial, in which the little black figure lay panting and apparently exhausted.

How awfully long did the remainder of this horrible night seem to the sick and phrensied wretch. He dared not again to resign himself to sleep, lest the terrific vision should re-appear; hardly too, did he venture to open his wearied eyes even in the dark, lest he should perceive the monstrous fiend squatted in some corner of the apartment. Yet did he shut his eyes but for a moment, he thought that it was again upon him, and started up with horror. He rang aloud for his attendants, but no one came, all was still as the grave; as for Lucretia he had not beheld her since he was first attacked by his disorder. Thus did he lay in a state of torturing horror, throughout the whole of that long, dreary night, the terror of which was increased, when he reflected that, if this single night appeared almost an eternity of terrors, what must seem the eternal night of hell, on which no day would ever dawn—that night to whose dreadful visions there would be no end?—He determined, at all events, upon getting rid of the fatal phial the very next morning.

When, however, the morning came, he felt his spirits so much revived, that he began to ask himself whether he had yet turned the bottle-imp sufficiently to account. Palace and villas, and all the luxuries wherewith they were furnished, seemed hardly enough; he, therefore, instantly demanded a great heap of ducats to be placed beneath his pillow, and, on finding them there instantaneously, he then began to reflect how best to dispose of the talisman. He knew that his physician was a great naturalist, and one who sought much after all monsters, and all such wonderful productions as are generally kept in spirits; he hoped, therefore, that he should be able to pass off the bottle-imp to the learned man as a curiosity of this description; for else the doctor was too good a christian to have any thing to do with the evil creature. The deceit indeed could hardly be termed an innocent one, but need knows no niceties.

Accordingly he offered the doctor the little spirit which was now become again exceedingly lively, jumping to and fro in the bottle with great vivacity; insomuch that, anxious to examine what he considered a wonderful lusus naturæ, the learned man agreed to purchase it, if the price demanded for it were not too high. In order to satisfy his conscience as well as he could, Richard asked a sum as nearly approaching to five ducats as was possible: the doctor, however, would give no more than three, which, fearing to lose his customer altogether, the other at last accepted, taking care, however, to bestow it all in alms upon the poor. But the money which he had found under his pillow, he carefully laid by, as the only fund upon which his future wealth and prosperity depended.

In the mean while, his disorder continued to increase; he lay in a constant delirium, and had he still been tormented by the possession of the bottle-devil, there is no doubt but that he would have actually died of terror and anxiety. At length, however, he gradually grew better; and now the only thing that seemed to retard his recovery, was his solicitude about the ducats, which he could no longer find beneath his pillow. At first he was very loth to make any enquiry after them; when, however, he did so, no one could give any account of them. Being able to obtain no information respecting the gold, it now remained for him to consider how he might best convert his mansion and villas into money. But here, too, he was reckoning without his host, for a throng of creditors appeared with various claims upon his estates, all duly signed by himse!f, and sealed with his own signet, he having, at the time of his boundless prosperity, given these papers to Lucretia to fill up as she judged proper: all that he could do, therefore, was to depart as quickly as possible with the little he could save from the fangs of these harpies; so that he quitted all his splendour very nearly a beggar.

At this juncture, his physician made his appearance, with a countenance betokening serious displeasure, “Doctor,” exclaimed the unfortunate young merchant, “if it so be, that you are come hither like the rest of your fraternity with a large bill, I prithee, add another item to the account, and see, good doctor, that it be for opium, or some equally potent drug: for my last bread is now baked, as I know but too well, I having no money to buy more.”

“Nay, nay,” replied the physician, “things are not yet so bad as that. I am not only ready to renounce every demand upon you, but have also prepared a certain, most efficacious medicine, that will quickly revive you from this despondency; all that I ask for it is, two ducats.”

“And most readily will I pay them,” replied the youth, which, having done, the doctor forthwith departed. On opening the box wherein he expected to find this cordial restorative, he discovered a phial, but how great was his dismay on perceiving that it was that which contained the little bottle-devil; and that, affixed to it, it had a label containing the following lines:

Thy body I strove to cure from ill,
But thou my soul hast sought to kill;
Yet, has my art, ’bove craft of thine,
Perceived full soon thy base design.
Let me then now retaliate,
To thee again revert thy fate:
Be thine once more the dreadful sprite;
And may’st thou feel his fellest might

Great, indeed, was Richard’s alarm, at finding that he had re-purchased his phial, at so much lower a price. The only consolation that now remained, was to employ it as an instrument of revenging himself upon his treacherous paramour, which he effected in the following manner.

Having first of all summoned by a wish, a sum of money double to that which he had lost, he carried and deposited it all with the nearest scrivener, excepting one hundred and twenty pieces, with which he betook himself to the abode of the faithless Lucretia. His reception was exactly such as he supposed that his gold would procure him: his mistress was as lavish of her caresses towards him, as she had ever been on any former occasion. After some time, he displayed the curious toy he had brought, making the little black puppet, inclosed in the phial, perform abundant antics and tricks. This, he informed Lucretia, was exactly like the one which she once flung into the water. She, like the rest of her sex, was desirous of obtaining such a droll plaything; and, on the youth’s sportively demanding a ducat for it, she paid it without hesitation. This bargain being completed, Richard hastened away as quickly as he could, and repaired to the scrivener, with whom he had deposited his money. He now found, however, that gold sticks so fast to certain people’s fingers, that they cannot shake it off. The honest man stared with the utmost astonishment, protesting most vehemently, that he had never clapped eyes on the young fellow before. This worthy specimen of probity, had written his receipt for the sum deposited with a kind of ink that totally disappeared in the space of a few hours: therefore, when Richard produced his voucher, he found that he had merely a piece of plain paper. He thus found himself suddenly reduced to poverty, and would, indeed, have been completely a beggar, had he not still thirty ducats remaining from what he had been squandering at Lucretia’s.

He who lies in too short a bed, must even pull up his legs; who has no bed, must couch on the bare floor; who cannot afford to ride, must walk:—so was it with our merchant, who was now fain to become a pedlar.

For this purpose he provided himself with a suitable box; but with what a heavy heart did he first buckle it on, to take his stand with some small ware in those very streets where, but a few weeks before, he used to pass with a splendid retinue. In a little while, however, he became somewhat reconciled to this new occupation, having no lack of customers. “If I proceed at this rate,” thought he, “I may yet again become a prosperous man, and that too at no very distant time. I will then return to my native Germany, where I shall find myself more comfortable than ever, after been in power of the accursed bottle-devil, and having got out of his clutches by my own skill and dexterity.”

With such thoughts did our newly-made pedlar cheer and console himself, on retiring for the night to an obscure inn. On his taking off his box, several of the guests, attracted by curiosity, began to examine the various wares it contained.

“My good friend,” exclaimed one of these inquisitive gentry, “prithee, what queer kind of animal is this which you have got here in this phial, and which keeps jumping about at so strange a rate?”

To his great terror Richard now, for the first time perceived, that along with the other articles in his box, he had purchased the fatal bottle-devil. Instantly did he offer it to the bystanders for a mere trifling sum, but not one of them could endure the hideous creature, neither could Richard inform them of any particular use it was of; he, nevertheless, continued to harass them at such a rate with his entreaties to purchase it, that, at length, they thrust the impertinent chapman and his wares into the street.

In the anguish of his distress he now returned to the person who had sold him the box, and pressed him to take back the little imp, at a lower price. The fellow, however, quite out of temper at being disturbed at such an unseasonable hour, and little disposed to become a dealer in such strange commodities, bade him begone, and take his trumpery to Lucretia, for she was the person that had lately sold him the stock of trinkets, among which was that queer-looking phial.

Without waiting to hear another syllable, Richard ran off to Lucretia, as quickly as if he had a devil driving him, instead of himself carrying a devil. He found the lewd creature along with a couple of gallants. At first they rated the uncourteous pedler for daring to intrude upon them; but afterwards they purchased nearly his whole stock, for Lucretia, had now recognized some of her old valuables, and also their present vendor: nor did the sight of him, in such a condition, seem by any means to damp her mirth. As to the bottle-imp, no one would purchase it; for Lucretia protested that she could not endure to look at the ugly thing.

“Say not so,” replied Richard, “my fair inconsiderate: permit me but to whisper in your ear some of its virtues, and, I am sure, you will hesitate no longer.”

She now retired a little aside, and the pedlar disclosed to her all the powerful, occult qualities, of his little bottle-imp.

“How now! thou cheating varlet,” cried the incredulous dame, “dost thou think to impose upon people by such fine tales as these. Were it true, I warrant me, thou hadst taken care first to provide thyself with something better than those filthy rags. Out with thee, for a knave! Begone, or I’ll denounce thee for a sorcerer and dealer in the black art: and then both thyself and thy devil may be burnt together.”

Both the gallants now took part in the fray, and kicked the unfortunate pedlar, and his wares, down stairs; whereupon, that the poor wight unable to resent the indignity, and terrified at the idea of being roasted for a wizard, hastened to leave Venice with all possible expedition; insomuch that, on the following day, he had quitted a territory which he now regarded as the land of all his misfortunes.

In the mean while he did not forget a nearer cause of his unhappiness, but, drawing the little dusky imp from his pocket, he cried:

“Thou miscreant devil! If I again call on thee for thy services, it is, that I may rid myself of thee for ever.”

Having thus vented the bitterness of his feelings, he forthwith desired to have a sum much more considerable than the last, and then, almost sinking under its weight, he proceeded to the next town. Here he purchased a splendid equipage, hired a numerous retinue, and set out for Rome, convinced that there he should soon be able to find some one, who would not scruple to take his unwelcome little companion off his hands. As often as he expended a ducat, did he require the imp to replace it by another, in order that, after selling his phial, he might still have the entire sum. This seemed to him no more than a fair compensation, for the horrors he constantly endured; for, in addition to the nightly visits of the black apparition, that never failed to come, and lay upon his breast, he saw also the bottle-devil constantly frisking about the phial, with the most horrible glee, as if now quite certain of his prey, at the expiration of the due period of his service.

Hardly had his wealth and the figure which he made, procured him admission into the first circles of Roman society, than his constant dread would not allow him to wait until a proper opportunity should offer, of freeing himself from his tormentor. He was continually offering his phial to every person, demanding for it three groschen in German money; insomuch that he, in a short time, became to be considered as a lunatic, and was a subject of ridicule to every one. Money makes a good mood, and many a fair friends withal: so was it with our Richard; yet no sooner did he produce his phial, and begin to talk of three groschens, than all present were glad to escape his importunity.

So great, at length, was his despair, that he could no longer endure to remain at Rome, but determined to try his fate in war, hoping that by some chance he might there, at least, get rid of the cause of his misery. He had heard, that two small Italian states were engaged in hostilities towards each other, and prepared to espouse the cause of one party. Adorned with a rich golden cuirass, and a superb crest of plumes, and armed with two light hunting pieces, an admirably tempered sword, and two beautiful daggers, did he set out, mounted on a noble Spanish steed, and attended by three followers, all of whom were bravely equipped.

A volunteer of so gallant a bearing, needed not to offer his services in vain. Richard soon saw himself, therefore, attached to a troop of brave comrades, and led such a jovial life in camp, with drinking and singing, that his mortal apprehensions, and nocturnal visions, gradually left him. Having received a good lesson from what he had experienced at Rome, he was now cautious in offering his strange ware to sale; observing not to urge it with such suspicious earnestness. Indeed, he had hardly spoken of it to any one, hoping thereby to have an opportunity of meeting with some who would not refuse it, if offered quite unawares, and with seeming indifference.

One morning, as Richard was playing at dice with some companions, they were suddenly summoned to battle, by an alarm sounded on the trumpet. The cry was instantly “to horse!” With joyous spirits did our warrior leap upon his steed as it neighed and pawed the ground: the leaders, encouraged on their troops, the signal sounded for the combat. A troop of the enemy’s cavalry advanced, apparently for the purpose of hindering their attack: yet they soon retired before the powerful charge of their adversaries, nor were Richard and his followers the last among the pursuers. The balls now began to whiz in the air, and many a rider fell from his horse, rolling to the earth in his blood. Spite of his personal courage, Richard could not think without shuddering of the immediate peril in which he was placed, fearing that some fatal ball might, in a single moment, deliver him into the power, not only of the bottle-devil, but of the great Satan himself.—Scarcely, however, had he expressed a wish to escape from the scene of danger, ere his steed bore him away to a wood, which was situated at no great distance.

So hard did he spur the animal, and urge him to flight, that it at length stopped quite exhausted. He then alighted, being himself greatly fatigued; unbuckled his own cuirass and sword, and the trappings of his horse, and laying himself down on the grass, said: “This fighting is dangerous work at the best, but much more so with a devil in one’s pocket!” He now wished to devise what course it would behove him next to pursue, but fell into a profound sleep.

After he had indulged in a repose of several hours, he was awakened by the sound of voices and approaching footsteps. He stirred not, in hope that he might be passed by unnoticed, but soon found that the attempt would not succeed, for a voice, of no very friendly or musical tone, thundered out: “Ho! Fellow, art thou already dead, or are we to have the honour of killing you?” Looking up perforce at this uncourteous address, the unfortunate Richard perceived a musket levelled at his breast. The fellow who held it, was a ruffianly-looking foot-soldier, and the others had already seized upon his steed and equipments as their booty. Struck with terror, he supplicated most earnestly for mercy, but if they were determined upon shooting him, requested that one of them would first purchase a little phial, which he had in his pocket.

“Senseless poltroon that thou art!” cried one of the fellows, with a grin, “to suppose that we here barter for any thing; although that we will take the bargain off thy hands, thou needest not fear:” and so saying, he seized hold of the phial, and thrust it into his bosom.

“In God’s name thou art welcome to it,” cried Richard, “if thou canst keep it. Yet that thou canst not do, unless thou first purchase it.”

The soldiers laughed at hearing him speak thus, and, thinking him somewhat crack-brained, rode off without paying farther attention to him. On feeling in his pocket, however, Richard found that the phial was there again, whereupon holding it up that they might see it, he called after them. The fellow who had taken it was struck with amazement; and as, on thrusting his hand into his bosom, he did not feel it, he ran back in order to recover his booty.

“Did I not tell thee,” said Richard mournfully, “that it would not continue with thee. Pay me but the trifle I demand, and it is thy own.”

“Juggler!” returned the soldier, “dost thou think to defraud me of my well-earned spoils, by these conjuring tricks of thine?”

And holding the phial carefully in his hand, away he ran to overtake his companions: suddenly, however, he stopped short, exclaiming, with an oath, that it was gone again. Whilst he was searching for it on the ground, Richard called out to him once more: “Return hither, my good friend, for it is again in my pocket.”

On finding this really to be the case, the soldier became more desirous of possessing so curious and wonderful a thing. On these occasions indeed it always manifested more than usual liveliness and agility, knowing that such bargains accelerated the final term of its servitude.—Three groschen, however, still seemed too much to the soldier. “Well then since thou art so unwilling to part with thy coin, let it be a single groschen, and take away thy purchase in good hour.” Thereupon was the bargain concluded, the money paid, and the little bottle-devil delivered up to his new master.—While the soldier and his companions were examining the singular creature, and amusing themselves with its grim antics, Richard was reflecting upon his future destiny. His heart now felt quite light; but unfortunately, his purse was quite as light as his heart; nor did he know to what to betake himself, since he would not venture to return to his troop, although he left there not only his followers and his equipments, but all his money. He was partly ashamed of his disgraceful flight, and partly afraid lest if he returned, he should be put to death as a deserter. It then occurred to him, that it would not be amiss were he to offer to accompany these troopers, having gathered from their discourse that they belonged to the other party, among whom he was certain of remaining unknown; and now that he had lost all his cash, and gotten rid of his little devil to boot, he felt that he had gotten back some of his courage in exchange, and was, by no means, disinclined to venture his life once again, in the hope of obtaining some valuable spoil. He accordingly gave utterance to his wishes; and his proposal being accepted, he forthwith set off with his new comrades.

The captain was not very scrupulous in taking into his service such a tall and well-built young fellow as Richard, who was therefore considered as fairly enlisted among them. He was still, however, displeased with his lot: for, since the last battle, the two armies remained quite inactive, without either attacking the other, a treaty of peace being in agitation. Under these circumstances, there was little danger of wounds, but, at the same time, very little opportunity of fattening on booty and plunder. Instead of the latter, the troops must perforce content themselves with their camp fare, and their scanty pay. In addition to this, while most of his comrades had already enriched themselves in the preceding engagements, Richard, the once wealthy merchant, was almost the only one who was a beggar among opulent neighbours. Very naturally, therefore, he grew weary of such a life, so that once having received his monthly pay—too inconsiderable for his wants, and yet too much for him not to attempt something with it—he determined to go to a suttling booth, and seek whether the dice would not befriend him more than either traffic or war had hitherto done.

His success at play was as chequered as usual, now winning, now losing: and so did it continue, until late at night, when all the dice turned up against Richard, whose cash was now quite gone, nor would any one give him credit for a doit. He now offered to stake his cartridges, having nothing else to offer; the proposal was accepted; and, as the throw was about to be made, Richard perceived that the soldier, who had accepted the stake, was the very same who had purchased the bottle-devil, by the assistance of which he would, doubtless, be certain of winning. He would fain have cried “Hold!” but the dice had already decided in favour of his opponent. Uttering curses at his ill fate, he quitted the company, and retired in the dark to his own tent. A comrade who had been equally unfortunate at play, but whose brain was less heated by wine, now took him by the arm, and, as they were proceeding together, enquired whether he had any more cartridges in his tent?

“No,” returned Richard, furiously, “did I possess any, they too should serve me for the same purpose.”

“Then,” said his companion, “you would do well to provide yourself with fresh ones, for should the commissary come to examine you, and find you without them, he will order you to be shot.”

“Zounds! that were plaguy work indeed!—but I have neither cartridges nor wherewithal to procure them.”

“Thine is a sorry case indeed then,” replied the other, “for the commissary comes hither on the morrow.”

This intelligence, although it did not tend greatly to tranquillize Richard, served in some degree to sober him: he went therefore to enquire of his comrades, if any one would lend him some cartridges. All, however, flouted him as a wild, idle fellow, and bade him not interrupt them with unseasonable stuff. In the utmost apprehension, lest he should be ordered to be shot the very next day, he rummaged every where, in the hope of finding some loose coin, but could meet with no more than five hellers. Late as it now was, he hurried from tent to tent in order to find some one who would supply him with the cartridges. Some laughed at, others abused him, but not one made any reply to his demand. At length, he came to a tent, the occupant of which he discovered to be the very soldier who had so lately stripped him of his cartridges at play.

“Comrade,” cried Richard, with great agitation, “if any one, it is yourself who must assist me in this extremity. But just now you plundered me of all my cartridges, nor is it the first time in my life, that you have proved the cause of my misfortunes. On the morrow the commissary comes, and he, unless I can produce my cartridges, will certainly give orders for me to be shot: you must therefore either give or lend,—at least sell me some.”

“As to either giving or lending, that I have long ago forsworn: yet, to ease your distress, I will agree to sell you some. What money therefore have you?”

“But five hellers,” replied Richard in a melancholy tone.

“Well,” said the soldier, “to shew thee that I am willing to do thee a comrade’s turn, there are five cartridges for thy five hellers.—Now then, betake thyself to thy rest, and disturb neither me nor my neighbours any longer;” which request, as soon as he had received what he sought, Richard instantly hastened to comply with.

On the following day, the troops were examined, and Richard passed muster with his five cartridges, at which he, for a while, considered himself supremely happy, in spite of all the misfortunes he had undergone. His felicity was, however, but of very short duration: the joy he at first felt, at finding himself out of actual danger, soon subsided, when, on retiring to his tent, he found himself obliged to dine off coarse bread, without any better sauce to it than his own reflections. “What would I not now give,” sighed he, “had I but one of all the ducats which in the days of my folly I so wantonly squandered away.”—Hardly had he formed the wish, when lo! a beautiful bright golden ducat was in his hand. But, alas! the thought of the bottle-devil, which instantly flashed across his mind, damped all the satisfaction he had otherwise felt, at finding himself possessor of so acceptable a piece of gold.

At this instant, the comrade of whom he had purchased the cartridges entered the tent, with a look of anxiety, and said: “Friend, I have missed the phial with the little black creature, you must remember it well; it is the same that I formerly purchased of yourself. Has it happened that I sold it to you by mistake for a cartridge, for I wrapped it up in a piece of paper, and it was lying close beside them?” With a trembling hand did Richard now search in his cartridge-box, and found, the first thing he took hold of, to be the fatal phial wrapped up in the form of a cartridge.

“Ha!” cried the soldier, “this is all right. To say the truth, ugly as the creature is, I should be exceedingly loth to lose it, since I somehow cannot help fancying that it helps me to good luck. So, comrade, take one of thy hellers back again, and return me my bottle.” Most readily did Richard accede to this demand, and the soldier departed equally pleased.

Yet was poor Richard ill at ease, after having met with his bottle-devil once more, and having had it again in his own possession, he could not help imagining that he saw it grinning at him, between the folds of his tent, and that it would strangle him in his sleep. Much as he stood in need of refreshment, he now flung the piece of money from him; and, at length his terror, lest the accursed being should once more return while he continued there, arose to such a pitch, that he fled from the camp, and entered a thick wood, where, exhausted by alarm and fatigue, he sunk down in a wild, lonesome spot.

“Ah me!” he exclaimed, as he lay there panting, “that I had but a camp bottle with water to keep me from dying with faintness!” And the bottle with the water stood beside him. It was not till after he had drank a hearty draught out of it, that he thought of asking himself by what means it came there. The bottle-devil now occurred to him; when, putting his hands into his pockets, and finding the phial there, overcome with sudden horror, he fell down in a deep swoon.

While he continued in this state, his former horrible dream returned, wherein he beheld the little bottle-imp stretch himself out longer and longer, and at last fix himself, grinning most hideously, upon his breast; he expostulated with the monster, asserting, that it no longer belonged to him, but the creature replied, with a hollow satanic laugh: “Thou bought me for a heller,—must therefore either sell me for less, or the bargain will not hold good.”

Richard leaped up in horror, and thought he still beheld the terrific figure, as it re-entered the phial in his pocket. In a state of agonized phrenzy, he dashed the phial from him down a steep hollow, but, instantly afterwards, felt it again in his pocket. “Alas! alas!” screamed the unhappy wretch, “how fortunate did I at one time consider myself, at finding, that let me cast away the phial ever so far, it always returned to me—but that it does so, is now my misery—yes, my everlasting misery.” And he, thereupon, began to run furiously among the wild bushwood, dashing in the dark against trunks of trees, and pieces of rock, and hearing, at every step he took, the phial clinking in his pocket.

At day break, he arrived at an open plain which had the appearance of being well cultivated, and had a cheerful appearance; somewhat revived by this prospect, he began to hope that what he had experienced, was merely a wild dream, and that the phial would prove to be no more than a common bottle. He took it out therefore, and held it up against the sun: but, alas! he still perceived the little black monster dancing up and down, and stretching out towards him as usual, its little ugly, mishapen arms, as if it would seize hold of him. Uttering a loud cry of agony, he let the phial fall on the ground, but only to feel it in his pocket immediately afterwards. The thing of the utmost consequence for him now to do, was to enquire every where for some coin of less value than a heller. Nowhere, however, could he meet with any such piece of money; so that, at length, despairing of being ever able to get rid of the monster that now threatened inevitably to become his master, he no longer thought of calling upon it for its services: his increasing horror on the contrary, would permit him to think of nothing but his miserable situation. Thus did he wander up and down, subsisting upon charity and alms; and as he had a wild, crazed appearance, and was continually beseeching every one for some piece of money less than a heller, he was considered as a madman, and was called, ‘Crazy Half-heller,’ by which appellation he was soon known far and wide.

It is said that the vulture sometimes fixes itself with its talons into the back of a young deer, and thus hunts to death the poor animal, which, as it flees, in agony, still carries along with it, its savage, relentless enemy. Thus was it with poor Richard, and the satanic imp in his phial:—but instead of accompanying him through his continual and unvaried misery, let us pass over a considerable interval and arrive at an important event.

He had one day lost himself in a wild rocky country, and had set down to rest beside a little stream, whose murmuring seemed to sympathize with his affliction. A loud sound of a horse’s feet rung on the rocky surface of the ground, when there came riding upon a large, black, wild-looking steed, a man of gigantic figure, and exceedingly terrific countenance; he was attired in a deep blood-red garment, and approached the spot where Richard was sitting.

“Wherefore so melancholy, young stranger?” said he addressing himself to the youth, who, involuntarily shuddered at his voice, as if with a vague presentiment of something evil;—“I should take thee to be a merchant:—hast thou then been making a bad bargain?—hast purchased any thing at too high a price?”

“Alas no! rather at too low a one,” returned Richard in a tremulous tone.

“Aye, so I should think indeed:” rejoined the grim horseman, with a horrible laugh. “And hast thou then got for sale a thing that they call a bottle-imp? Or am I mistaken in conjecturing you to be a crazy Half-heller?”

The poor youth was hardly able to reply “yes,” so great was his horror, expecting every instant to behold the apparition’s mantle expand itself into a pair of bloody wings, and his steed to assume a more terrific, spectral appearance, breathing forth infernal flames from its nostrils; and, lastly, that the monster would carry off his wretched soul to the regions of eternal misery.

But the ghastly horseman said, in somewhat milder voice, and with less appalling mien: “I perceive for whom you take me: yet be comforted, for I am not he, I rather present myself to rescue you, if so may be, from his power; having for some days past been searching for you, in order to become the purchaser of your phial. To confess the truth, my friend, thou hast paid indeed a most damnable small sum for it, nor can even I myself inform you where it is possible to meet a coin of less value. But, listen and obey me. On the other side of this mountain there resides a prince who is a sad dissolute young fellow. When he comes to the chase on the morrow, I will first withdraw him from his attendants, and then cause a frightful monster to fall upon him. Wait thou here till midnight, and then proceed, just as the moon rises above that jagged rock, towards that gloomy defile to the left, but neither hurry nor loiter in thy pace, so wilt thou arrive at the spot precisely as the monster has seized the prince in his frightful paws. Attack it, but courageously;—it must yield to thee; and drive it down the steep cliff into the sea. Then, as a recompense for having delivered him, demand of the prince that he cause two half hellers to be coined for thee; let me have them, in order that, with one, I may become the purchaser of thy bottle-devil.”

So spoke the grisly horseman, and then, without waiting for any reply, rode off slowly into the wood.

“But where am I to find thee when I have obtained the half-hellers?” cried out Richard.

“At the black fountain; of which each old crone hereabouts will be able to inform thee;” and then with solemn but wide outstretching pace did the horrible steed bear away its no less terrific rider.

He who has already lost nearly every thing, ventures not much by any further risk: Richard, therefore, determined, as his situation was so desperate, to follow the councils of the grisly spectre.

Night closed in, and the rising moon shortly after appeared above the craggy tops of the rocks which had been marked out to him. The pale wanderer then raised himself tremblingly, and entered the dark defile. All seemed there cheerless and gloomy; seldom was a pale moon-beam able to penetrate above the lofty precipices; a dark oppressive vapour too, as if exhaled from graves, seemed to fill the narrow pass; in other respects there was nothing particularly terrible in its appearance. Richard felt himself by no means disposed to linger in the gloomy valley, yet adhering to the strict injunction laid upon him by the mysterious horseman, he did not venture to quicken his pace, resolutely determined not to snap short at once the only slender thread that still attached him to light and hope.

After the lapse of several hours, some red streaks of dawn cast a glimmering light across his path; a reviving breeze played upon his forehead. But, just as he was about to emerge from the deep valley, and to enjoy the forest scenery, and the azure waters of the sea, that lay expanded at no great distance before him, he was disturbed by a piercing cry of distress. On looking around, he perceived a horrible animal attacking a youth in a magnificent hunting dress, who had fallen on the ground. Richard’s first impulse was to rush instantly to the stranger’s rescue; yet his courage failed him as soon as he clearly discerned the monster, and saw that it resembled a huge grisly baboon, with a stag’s antlers on its forehead; and, notwithstanding the cries of the wretched man for succour, he was about to turn back. But suddenly calling to mind all that the horseman had said, and inspired by the dread of his eternal doom, he ran and attacked the monster of an ape with a knotty club, just as it had seized the unfortunate hunter in its paws to fling him up into the air, and then catch him upon his branching horns as he descended to the ground. At the approach of Richard, however, it let fall its prey, and began to flee with a hideous, terrifying cry; he pursuing it all the while, till, leaping from a precipice into the sea, it turned its frightful visage upon him, and then disappeared beneath the waves.

Flushed with success, the youth now returned triumphantly to the hunter whom he had just rescued, and who, as he expected it would be, announced himself as the prince of that territory. After extolling the bravery of his deliverer, he requested that he would boldly demand whatever boon he should think fit.

“What!” exclaimed Richard, in a transport of joyous hope, “and are you serious? and will you pledge me your princely word that you will grant what I shall demand of you?”

Again the prince confirmed his promise, assuring him, in the most solemn manner, that he would gladly comply with whatever he should request.

“Then, I supplicate you, for the love of God, to order that some half-hellers be immediately struck for me, even though it be only two.” Whilst the prince was regarding his strange petitioner with fixed astonishment, some of his train came up, and, on hearing the adventure, and the singular boon that had been craved, one of them recognized, in the person of the suitor, the poor crazed Half-heller.

The prince began thereupon to laugh, whilst Richard, clasping his knees, conjured him in the most moving manner, protesting that, unless he obtained the half-hellers, his soul was doomed to everlasting perdition.

To this the prince replied, while he still continued to laugh, “Rise up, my friend, I have pledged my princely word, and, if you persist in demanding them, I will engage to supply thee with half-hellers to thy very heart’s content. But, if a still lesser coin will suit your purpose, I can accommodate thee without the aid of my mint-master, for the neighbouring provinces all maintain that my hellers are so light that three of them are requisite to pass for a single ordinary one.”

“Were that, indeed, the case—” said Richard. “Thou art indeed the first,” returned the prince, “that has ever doubted it. Should they, however, upon trial, prove not suitable for your purpose, I here promise to order some less valuable to be coined for your especial use—provided, however, that it be possible so to do.”

Having said this, he gave orders that Richard should forthwith receive a whole bagfull of hellers. The latter instantly set off at a furious rate towards the adjoining province, where he became more delighted than he had been with any occurrence for a long time past, at finding, at the very first inn, that the people were exceedingly unwilling to exchange one heller in return for three which he offered them, by way of experiment.

He now enquired his way towards the Black Fountain, when some children, who were present, ran away, shrieking with affright; and the host informed him, not without shuddering himself, that it was a place frequented by demons and evil spirits, but hardly ever visited by mortal being. He knew perfectly well, however, that the entrance to it was at no very great distance, through a cavern, at the mouth of which stood two decayed cypress trees, so that Richard could not mistake finding it; ‘yet, God forbid, that he, or any other Christian person, should ever seek it!’

At hearing this account, Richard was again greatly disturbed, but let the event be what it would he must make the attempt, and therefore set out to discover it. Even at a distance, the cavern had a most dismal and terrifying appearance: it seemed as if the two cypresses had died with horror at the ghastly hollow, which, as he approached it, displayed just above its mouth, a singular stone. It seemed to be entirely covered with grim countenances, some of which, bore a resemblance to the hideous baboon-monster on the sea-shore. Yet, on looking fearlessly and attentively, one might perceive that it was merely the rugged stone. Not without trembling, did Richard pass beneath these horrible visages. The bottle-imp now became so heavy in his pocket, that it seemed as if it wished to prevent his advancing further. This circumstance inspired him with courage to proceed: “for,” thought he, “it behoves me to do that which this creature wishes I should not do.” On penetrating farther into the cavern, the darkness became so great, that he could no longer discern any terrifying shapes. He now proceeded, with the utmost caution, groping his way with a stick lest he should fall into some abyss, yet found nothing but a soft, mossy turf; and had he not heard at times, a strange groaning noise, his fears would have ceased altogether. At length, he reached the outlet of the cavern. He now found himself in a dreary hollow, quite inclosed by steep hills. On one side, he perceived the large sable steed of the mysterious customer for his phial, which was standing motionless as a brazen statue. Opposite to him was a spring gushing from the rock, and in this, the grim horseman was washing both his face and hands. But the horrid stream was of an inky hue, with which it stained whatever it touched; for when the gigantic figure turned round towards Richard, the latter perceived that his visage was become like that of a Moor, and thereby formed a terrific contrast against his blood-red garments.

“Shudder not,” cried the hideous being “this is only one of the ceremonies which I am obliged to perform in honour of the devil. Each Friday am I bound to wash myself thus, in scorn of him whom ye call your God. I am also compelled to stain my garment afresh with my own blood—it is this which gives it a hue of so much deadly lustre:—besides a number of still more horrible ceremonies which I am obliged to undergo. I have, moreover, formed so strong a compact with the powers of darkness both for body and soul, that it is now utterly impossible for me to obtain redemption on any terms. And what do you imagine are the terms on which I have sold myself?—for a hundred thousand pieces yearly. Thus seeing how desperate is my own condition, still I am willing to serve thee, by purchasing the imp thou carriest in thy phial, and thus to frustrate the end of all his long servitude; besides, the rescuing thee from the powers of hell, will so enrage them, that, reckless of ought else, I’ll do it. Then how will their impotent curses peal through the vaults of deepest hell; ha! ha! ha!” So saying, he began to laugh in the most frightful manner, that the very rocks re-echoed, and the sable steed, which had hitherto stood motionless, seemed to shrink with terror at the awful sound.

“Now then, friend,” added he, after a while, “hast thou brought me any half-hellers?”

Upon Richard’s shewing him his purse, he took three of the pieces and gave him a heller in exchange; one of which he directly paid back again, as the purchase money for the bottle-devil, that now lay crouched up melancholy at the bottom of the phial, so that he felt quite heavy. At perceiving this, the unknown purchaser laughed again most violently, and exclaimed, “Nothing can avail thee, fiend: all resistance is in vain. In token, therefore, of thy obedience, let me have instantly as much gold as my strong steed can bear.’ And no sooner had he uttered the command, than the enormous beast stood panting beneath the golden load. Then the blood-red horseman having mounted on its back, it began to crawl up the perpendicular sides of the rock, just as a fly does up a wall;—and disappeared for ever.

Richard stood for some minutes fixed to the spot in a stupor of astonishment and joy; but the air of that Stygian recess seemed troublous and heavy, while a hollow voice issuing from the dusky waves of the Black Fountain, exclaimed: “Now then are all our labours frustrated, for he who while doomed to destruction could attempt the rescue of another may even yet be saved himself.” 1 Struck with horror at the sounds, although exulting at their import, Richard rushed again through the cavern to feel again the atmosphere of heaven.

He now felt assured that he was delivered of his evil fiend for ever, and looked once more on the face of nature with feelings that had long been strangers to his bosom. Throwing himself upon the grass, he gazed in an extasy of delight on the pure, tranquil, sunny sky, while a warm gush of tears expressed that rapture and that gratitude for which he could find no words. The young merchant now became light and gay as an innocent boy, yet without any thing resembling his former levity. Without boasting, as he might well have done, how he had contrived to outwit the powers of hell, he devoted himself henceforth to the service of heaven, and soon found himself thriving far greater prosperity, from the efforts of honest industry, than he had even enjoyed by means of the fatal talisman. And, whenever he used afterwards to relate to his awe-struck grand-children the adventures of his early days, after uttering a pious orison for the soul of his deliverer, he would add, by way of moral to his tale, “Lust not, my dear children, after ill-gotten and ill-to-be used mammon, for it is the Bottle-Imp, that serves us to our own destruction.”

The translator has given a somewhat different form to the conclusion of the tale, so as to render it more satisfactory, by not leaving it to be conjectured that the being by whom Richard is saved, is himself allied irrecoverably to the powers of darkness, else, it should seem, that he would rather have hastened the final perdition of another.

The following extraordinary occurrence is said to have befallen Berthold, a young German merchant, and though hardly accredited, in all its details, is worthy of repetition on many accounts. Being engaged in speculations of considerable extent, which compelled him to bear about his person a capital of no small amount, in gold, jewels, and other valuables, he was not a little alarmed on perceiving, at the close of day, that he had lost himself amid the intricacies of one of our native mountain forests, and that night was rapidly surrounding him in the middle of a gloomy valley, and in a road to which he was an utter stranger. It was quite evident that he had chanced upon a remote and unfrequented defile; for the forest deer no longer evinced any shyness at his presence, and the flight of the owls, as they circled round his person, became so daring and undisturbed, that he frequently gave an involuntary bend of his head and shoulders, as a protection from the flapping and rustling of their wings. At length he perceived a man pacing the footpath a little before him; and whom, on enquiry, he found to be a collier residing in the forest. Our traveller’s request of a lodging for the night, and a promise of safe conduct in the morning, was acceded to, and given with so much frankness and alacrity, that every feeling of rising suspicion was subdued, and the parties arrived at the collier’s cottage, mutually satisfied with their covenant. On their arrival, the collier’s wife made her appearance with a light at the door, behind her stood a range of youthful, chubby faces, her children; and the light, as it fell upon the person of the host, exhibited one of those honest, manly countenances, which happily are still to be met with in abundance among the peasantry of our native country.

The whole family, together with their guest, now entered a warm and cheerful sitting-room, and ranged themselves around a fire, upon the hearth: and our traveller began to feel as little concern for his wealth, as if he had reached his paternal dwelling, and were surrounded by his brothers and sisters. He had merely removed his cloak-bag from his horse; and, having confided the faithful creature to one of the collier’s sons for food and a stall, he threw his valuable package into a corner of the apartment, and, though he retained his sword by his side, and his pistols at his belt, this was more from the habitual caution induced by a traveller’s life, than from any chance that such things might be wanted here. The conversation soon became general. The traveller talked of the countries he had seen; the collier spoke of the forest and his occupations; and the rest of the family occasionally joined in with pertinent questions or modest remarks. In the mean time a jug of nut-brown ale was introduced; the toast of welcome and wishes for better acquaintance was drunk; the cheerful group proceeded from conversation to more social tokens of joy; and the song became substituted for adventure or story. The collier’s children were in the midst of a lively glee, when a strange tapping was heard at the door. A knock was given with the finger so very, very gently: yet, notwithstanding the seeming lightness of the pressure, the feeble sound was distinctly heard in the room, and rose above the clear and mirthful voices of the children. The singing was instantly at an end; the whole family assumed a serious and solemn expression of manner; while the collier, in a friendly tone, exclaimed: “Come in, Father! in heaven’s name come in!”

The door now opened, and a little decent looking old man crept quietly in. He saluted the family circle with an air of kind good nature, and only stopped to gaze in astonishment at the stranger. In a short time he drew towards the table and placed himself in the lowest seat; which, in fact seemed to have been purposely left for him. Berthold’s astonishment was equally great as that expressed by the old man. For this singular personage was dressed in a costume of earlier days; but, though the form bespoke an existence in times gone by, there was nothing of this kind in the material, since the whole dress exhibited marks of great attention to neatness and decency. In addition to this, his person, as already observed, was remarkably small: at first sight, his countenance might be said to be composed and pleasing, but, on closer observation, it was found to contain evident traces of secret sorrow. The family treated him as an old acquaintance, though with manifest signs of compassion. Berthold would have willingly asked, if the old man were a relation,—the collier’s father or perhaps his wife’s—and whether his pale and melancholy countenance were the effect of indisposition;—but, as often as he attempted to open his mouth, the old man looked at him with a half startled, half angry expression, and that in so particular a manner, that he always felt his curiosity checked, though greatly increased.

At length, the old man folded his hands, as if inclined for prayer; looked across to the collier’s seat, and cried in a hoarse voice:—“Come! if you can, let us have the evening prayer.”

The collier instantly began the fine old hymn:

“The forest now is hush’d in rest,”

in which he was joined by his wife and children; the old man united his voice to theirs, and sang with a power and clearness which made the cottage peal again, and must have excited strong surprize in any one, not accustomed to hear him. At first Berthold was unable to join in the chorus, from pure agitation and astonishment. This appeared to make the old man both angry and alarmed; he constantly eyed our traveller with strange dissatisfied looks, and the collier also, admonished his guest by earnest and expressive gestures, that he ought to follow the common example. This Berthold was, at length, able to do, Every thing now was correct and devotional, and, after a few more additional prayers and hymns, the old man took his departure with a humble and courteous deportment. He had already closed the door, and was about to let the latch fall, when he suddenly dashed it open, cast a wild and terrific look on Berthold, and as speedily slammed it together.

“Humph!” said the collier, with some surprise, as he now turned to apologise to his guest for his conduct, “this is not his usual behaviour.”

Berthold rejoined, by supposing the old gentleman to be a little disordered in his mind.

“Why, that,” said the collier, “it is impossible to deny; but still, he is perfectly harmless and never does any one an injury. At least, we have never had the slightest proof of such misconduct for a very long time. I should, however, tell you, that the only room in which I can accommodate you, has no proper fastening to it; and it often happens, that the old man finds his way in there. But you need not disturb yourself—and do not interfere with him—he will soon retreat of his own accord. Besides, I fancy you are too much fatigued to be roused by any of his proceedings; and, as you must have already observed, he moves with extreme gentleness and silence. Berthold assented to all the collier advanced with a smiling countenance, but he felt widely different at heart to the sensations previously existing in his bosom, though without being able to account exactly for the change; and, as the collier led the way up the narrow stair-case, which conducted him to his chamber; he irresistibly felt disposed to grasp his cloak-bag with a firmer hold, and keep a constant eye upon his sword and pistols.

The collier having suspended the lamp in a place of safety, and commended his guest to the protection of heaven for the night, speedily withdrew. But Berthold left alone in his narrow chamber, pervious to the wind in every direction, seemed to feel as if the pious benediction would, somehow or other, fail of its effect. It was a long time since he had felt so disturbed and troubled in his mind. He immediately retired to bed, seemingly exhausted with the fatigues of the day, but sleep was not to be thought of. He now conceived his cloak-bag too remote from him; now his arms excited the same apprehensions, and now again, both were hardly sufficiently near. Under such excitements he frequently rose, and if for an instant sleep visited his eyes, he started up again at every breeze of wind, with interchanging fears and hopes of great misfortune, or equally unexpected and surprising good luck. All his commercial plans and speculations became ravelled into one interminable web of confusion, from which it was impossible to extricate himself, or to separate one single and individual thought from the mazes into which his drowsiness had woven it. In addition to this, he felt an overwhelming and all-engrossing thirst for gain, excited by the difficulties around him; and it was a considerable time before these perplexities rocked him into a sleep, which perhaps, with more propriety, might be called a swoon.

It might be about midnight, or a little after, when Berthold thought he heard a gentle movement and rustling in his chamber. But fatigue, had so completely mastered him, that he lay motionless in his bed; and, if at times he raised his unwilling eye-lids, and seemed to perceive the little old man passing backwards and forwards near his bed, his drowsy sense only assured him, that the whole was mere fancy; and besides, had not the collier apprized him of all this, previous to his going to bed? At length, however, these interruptions became too frequent; a sudden fright thoroughly roused him from every sleepy feeling; he started up in his bed, and beheld the little old man of the preceding evening, snugly throned upon his cloak-bag, and looking towards him with a sort of scornful pity.

“Villain!” exclaimed Berthold in a tone of mingled rage and fear. “Let go my property!” The abruptness of this address, appeared to startle the old man. He hastened towards the door, seemingly muttering an uneasy prayer, and suddenly disappeared.

Berthold’s first object was to examine his cloak-bag, and learn whether any thing had been taken from it. He was little disposed to consider the old man a thief, but the diseased and crazy mind of this singular being, might have found amusement in exchanging the contents for rubbish, or in destroying many important papers, with which it was charged. The locks and straps appeared untouched, and even after they were opened, every thing was found in the same condition it was left. Still, however, Berthold’s mind was not to be tranquilized: something might have fallen out by the way, something might have suffered by the journey, and under this impression, he examined every separate package, now rejoicing at the extent of his wealth, and now regretting that it was no greater. In the midst of this occupation, he was suddenly disturbed by a puff of air upon his cheek. At first, he conceived it to be merely a current of wind which found its way through an aperture in the window; and he accordingly only folded his mantle more closely round him. The puff was now repeated: it became more distinct and perceptible, and as he turned with displeasure towards the quarter from whence it appeared to proceed; this feeling became changed into horror, on perceiving the little old man’s face, quite close to his own.

“What do you want here?” exclaimed Berthold; “creep to your bed, and warm yourself.”

“In bed I only get colder and colder, and I do so like to see such pretty things as you have got. But I know where there are much prettier, aye much, much prettier!”

“What is that you say?” enquired Berthold, who now began to fancy that the extraordinary good fortune which had floated before him, while half asleep, was to be realized by the use of this crazy being.

“If you would but come,” sighed the old man: “down below there, down through the forest, and beside the moor.”

“Why with you,” said Berthold, “I suppose I might venture without much risk. The old man now turned towards the door, and said:

“Only let me get my mantle. I will be back in an instant, and then we will go together.”

Berthold had little time to reflect on his promise, for the old man had scarcely quitted the room, before the latch was raised again, and in stalked a man, immoderately tall and spare, with a large scarlet mantle thrown across his shoulders, a huge sword under one arm and a musket over the other. Berthold instantly laid hand upon his pistols.

“Why aye,” said the man in red, “you may as well take those with you; only make all the haste you can, that we may get out into the wood.”

“With you?” exclaimed Berthold, “I am not going with you. Where is the little old man?”

“Hey day! do but look at me;” rejoined the other, as he removed the mantle from before his face. Berthold now perceived a close resemblance between this terrific phantom, and the little old man; in fact, so great, that the only difference seemed to consist in the mere expression of feature, for what wore a meek and humble air in the one, was wild and ferocious in the other. Berthold felt assured that both he and his treasure were betrayed; and he, therefore, exclaimed in a firm voice: “On any future occasion, when you may chose to dispatch your simple brother for the purpose of seducing people into your net; I think it would be quite as well not to disturb the illusion, by making this senseless exhibition of your own person. I therefore tell you, at one word, I am not going with you, and nothing shall make me.”

“Indeed!” said the man in red, “you won’t go?”

“No!”—

“Why then I’ll make you:” and with this he stretched out his long bony arm towards our traveller, who, in a paroxysm of fear and tremor, fired his pistol. The house below now became alive and bustling; the collier was distinctly heard ascending the staircase with hasty step, and the man in red with reverted head and towards Berthold, darted out at the door. “In the name of heaven,” exclaimed the collier, as he burst into the room, “what have you done to our Brownie?”

“Your Brownie?” stammered Berthold, as he looked at his host with astonishment. For his previous idea of unbounded wealth still floated before his fancy; and finding now that he was evidently not to gain any, he half thought it must be his chance to lose some, and that the whole house had conspired against him.

The collier, however, continued; “He passed me on the stairs, most unusually tall and angry, and wrapt in his red mantle, with his sword and gun.”

Perceiving now that Berthold was unable to comprehend what he said, he begged his guest would descend to the room below, where every body had assembled from alarm at the firing, and he would there endeavour to tranquilize both his family and the stranger. Berthold complied with his host’s request, taking his cloak-bag under his left arm, his remaining loaded pistol in his right hand, and his other weapons in his belt. His only motive for going below, was the idea of being nearer the house-door than in his present confined chamber. As he entered the sitting-room, the whole family seemed to regard him with an eye of suspicion, and there was a manifest difference in his present reception, from that given him a few hours before. The collier now addressed his guest in the following terms:

“When I first took this cottage, our Brownie was accustomed to wander about in the same terrific form, in which you have seen him this evening. On this account the house had long been abandoned, and no one was found sufficiently venturous to live in it, or in fact in the neighbouring district of the forest. For the power of these spirits has rather an extensive circle. My predecessor was not only very rich, but very avaricious, and his passion for gold induced him to bury his money in the country around, and it was his constant practice, during his life, to roam about the spot where his treasure lay concealed. On such occasions he usually wrapt himself up in a red mantle, carried a sword and gun on his shoulders, for the purpose of scaring the robbers, as he declared, who might mistake his person for the city executioner. At his death, he was unable to communicate the spot where his money was deposited; it is possible he may have forgotten it, and it was, perhaps, on this account his mind became so distracted, and that he assumed this frightful attire.

“I, however, said to myself: “a pious heart, and constant exercise in prayer, is a sufficient protection against even Satan himself, much less against a poor crazy goblin; and with this feeling I brought my wife and children to our new habitation. At first, it must be confessed, our friend in the red mantle caused us a good deal of trouble; for when a man is going about on his own concerns, and solely occupied with these and similar thoughts, it is enough to startle even the most courageous, to find some monstrous thing starting up before him, and that too of the goblin tribe. The children suffered exceedingly, and even my wife was frequently overpowered with fright and alarm.”

“Yes!” sobbed the wife, “and now these terrific times will be renewed. It was but just now that he looked in at the door, with a wild and angry countenance, taller than ever, and wrapt in his frightful red mantle.”

“Do as you did before;” said the collier, “be constant in prayer, and humble devotion; let all your thoughts be pure and pious, and nothing will harm you.”

At this instant the latch of the door was raised up and down with a violent and continued motion; the whole assembly pressed closer together, and the children wept aloud. The collier alone advanced with a firm and intrepid step, and cried out: “In the name of the Most High, I charge thee to depart: we are beyond thy power.” A noise was now heard without, like the passage of a whirlwind through the house; and the collier, as he resumed his seat, continued in the following manner:

“At that time we considered it a trial, it may, perhaps, be ordained us as such now. We have only to pray with greater zeal; to keep a more scrupulous watch over our actions. We certainly had managed to make him lay aside his red mantle, to conduct himself with decency, to attend our regular evening prayer, to compose his features into something like complacency, and to reduce his form into a very diminutive size, as if his decreasing limbs would eventually disappear from the earth, and the poor creature betake himself to rest until the awful day of doom. Children! as a quiet, meek and fearful Brownie, he wan your affections; it always gave you pain that in his extreme contrition, he chose to take the lowest seat at our evening prayers. You must now cheerfully labour for his and your own repose, by patience, prayer and purity of heart. We shall soon bring him to the same condition in which he was last night.”

The family now rose, and promised to obey their father’s instructions; to maintain the struggle against the spirit of evil with undiminished resolution, in whatever form it might choose to appear.

Berthold’s mind, however, was in the most agitated and distracted state. He first conceived himself seized with a fit of delirium, and that all these extraordinary circumstances were the mere fancies of a disordered imagination; he then believed that the whole was a trick devised to make a fool of him; and now thought he had fallen among a band of hypocritical thieves, and that every thing had for its object the possession of his property. Amidst these conflicting ideas, he demanded his horse. The collier’s eldest son instantly ran to the stable to prepare it, and his father observed: “You had better remain till the day-light: at this hour of the morning the forest is dangerous, and even haunted.”

Our traveller, however, persisted in his determination; and he soon perceived that the whole family were glad at heart with the prospect of being relieved of his company, and that the collier had only pressed his stay from motives of common hospitality. His proffer of payment for the evening’s repast and lodging, was rejected with so much firmness, and apparent displeasure, that he abstained from pressing the unwelcome tribute. His horse now appeared at the door, his cloak-bag was soon bestowed in its wonted place; Berthold sprang into the saddle, and took leave of his singular host with thanks, but coldly received, and with a conviction that his departure had occasioned more joy than his arrival. With a misgiving mind, and many anxious doubts, he now pursued the course which had been pointed out to him.

He found it quite impossible to believe that the inhabitants of the cottage were right, and that the Brownie was wrong; for said he, if this creature be not a spirit, it is clear they are a pack of cheats; and if it be, the poor thing is doing nothing more than its duty, in revealing the spot of its secret deposit, and committing to some mortal for use and enjoyment, what is now lying unemployed. The trees now appeared to assume an unusual and singular form; the morning breeze as it whistled beside him, seemed to be charged with notes of golden promise; the mist began to shape itself into a lofty arcade about him, and as our traveller rode beneath it, the thought shot across his mind: “Nature herself is linked in compact with me, and if this be the case, no illusion can intercept my happy career.”

“Luck’s all!” he shouted aloud: and had scarcely spoken the words, before he perceived the man in red walking beside him, and apparently giving a nod of approbation, both to his words and thoughts. At first he felt a little uneasy; but the more he reflected on the reasons for suppressing his alarm, the more the red mantled stranger seemed to nod in friendly approbation of his conduct, and at length began to address him in the following manner:

“To tell you the truth comrade, I began to be heartily sick of these collier people. That eternal singing and praying reduced me down to nothing; you saw yourself, what a miserable little shrivelled creature I was become—but as soon as you came, though I was rather fierce at first as if something strange had arrived—yet we soon understood each other, and then I grew—aye, and I can grow too till my head touches yonder starry canopy. Why if you would but entertain the aspiring thoughts you ought, and fancy yourself standing above there, quite a different sort of a fellow, to other mortals, a fellow endowed by nature with all her riches and gifts, free from trouble and toil, you would then be just what I wish you: and moreover the treasure should be yours. The collier’s people are far too stupid for such things.—Come! shall we dig?”

Berthold nodded assent, and the man in red pointed to a small hillock at a little distance, strewed with the leaves and cones of the pine-tree. As our traveller was wholly unprovided with implements for digging, he was compelled to turn up the earth with his sword; but his labour was not a little checked by fear as he perceived the man in red join in the work, and wherever he fixed his hand, a blue sulphureous vapour rose from the earth.

The vapour continued to rise; the earth groaned, the stones rolled impetuously forward and at last two urns were discovered, which were no sooner exposed to the morning air than they instantly crumbled into dust. It was quite in vain that Berthold continued his researches—no treasure was to be found. The man in red now evinced considerable uneasiness; he expressed his sorrow by ringing his long bony hands, and at length pointed to a neighbouring hillock.

Berthold applied himself here with the same ardour as before, and with the same result—he found nothing but earthen pots, ashes and rubbish. They proceeded from one hillock to another, still eager in the pursuit, but all exhibited the same contents, the same unprofitable harvest. The spirit now became filled with rage, he dashed his bony fists against the surrounding trees, (which at every blow emitted a stream of sulphureous sparks) and at last accused his companion of having discovered the treasure in the first hillock, and surreptitiously secreted it. Berthold stood aghast and trembling before the angry phantom, whose person suddenly glowed in one continued flame of red, and rose as his indignation swelled, far above the tops of the adjoining trees. At this instant the cock crowed. With a cry of deep resentment and agonized suffering, the goblin vanished into air, and the morning bell of a neighbouring village was distinctly heard, to the great relief and joy of our traveller. Terrified beyond expression at the danger he had escaped, Berthold now sought his equally terrified horse, and which at the commencement of his labours he had bound to a tree; and having thrown himself into the saddle, galloped rapidly forwards towards the nearest habitations of men.

Years now rolled on, during which, Berthold engaged in extensive and important commercial pursuits, passed his life in foreign lands, and amidst a round of constant and anxious occupation. But varied as were the objects which necessarily pressed upon his attention, be never forgot his adventure with the man in red, and the evening spent with the collier’s family. It constantly reverted to his imagination, sometimes with feelings of dread and curiosity, sometimes of excited, half satisfied anxiety; and as he was on his return home, and approached the neighbourhood, he resolved upon retracing his former route, and having discovered the unfrequented path, arrived at the close of day before the collier’s lonely cottage.

This arrival, like that of former years, brought the same healthy, honest faces at the door; the collier’s wife appeared with her lamp, carefully guarding it against the current which threatened to extinguish it; and the collier himself, advanced towards our traveller, with friendly expressions of welcome. The stranger was now invited in; his horse was committed to one of the sons; but the recognition of his person seemed to check in all, except his host, the pleasure with which the benighted traveller was ever received by the collier’s family.

The room wore much the same aspect as before; the whole party were soon seated round the family table; the jug of ale was brought forth and circulated; but to Berthold’s great alarm, the seat formerly occupied by the goblin, was still left vacant, as if his presence were expected with every returning evening. Besides this, little was said; both parties viewed each other with looks of suspicion, and that which had formed the best part of our traveller’s entertainment—friendly converse, and the joyous song was now wholly wanting.

At length the collier addressed his guest in the following manner:

“We know not what may have passed between you and our Brownie some years ago; but the consequences to us were difficulty, toil, fear, and anxiety. You are now about to pass another night under our roof, and I can only wish from my very heart, that your mind may be inclined to pure and grateful devotion; that you may disturb neither us or our Brownie. As far as regards him, indeed, it is not very likely that you will produce any pernicious effects upon his repose; although your head and your heart may still be devoted to gain and gold.—But hush! children—the hour of prayer is come.”

The whole family now folded their hands; the collier rose with uncovered head, and again began the fine old hymn:—

“The forest now is hush’d in rest.”

Berthold, with true devotional feelings, joined in the chorus, expecting every moment, the Brownie’s appearance, although in his former quiet garb and figure. But no finger tapped at the door—no one entered; a gentle light alone was seen in the room, and a soft melodious sound was heard, like the notes of musical glasses, when touched by the finger slightly wetted.

Prayers were scarcely over, before Berthold inquired the cause of the light and the sounds.

“’Tis our Brownie,” replied the collier; “he never announces himself now, in any other manner. But to effect this, we have found it necessary to persevere in prayer, and to keep a careful guard over the purity of our hearts.”

There was something in Berthold’s bosom, which told him he was not worthy of passing the night here. He asked for his horse, though in a more friendly tone than formerly; it was soon brought him by the collier’s eldest son, in a manner equally friendly; and the family bade him farewell, perceiving that his departure was not occasioned by an evil disposition, and instructed him in his road, which he now pursued with far different thoughts than when he travelled it before. He perceived nothing supernatural in his way; except that a beautiful stream of light occasionally rose before him, and shed a most agreeable and brilliant radiance over the shrubs and plants of the forest.

This story contains much that is fabulous—it may possibly be a fable; but he who would chuse to regard it as nothing more, would be equally unjust to the Author, himself, and the good old Cause.

In a fertile district of Silesia, situated at the foot of the Ogre mountains, a party of relations were collected together, a short time before the peace of Westphalia, for the purpose of dividing the property of a wealthy farmer, who had died without children, and whose large estates lay scattered about in the neighbouring country. In furtherance of this object, the several claimants were assembled in the principal inn of the village, and the adjustment of their respective shares would soon have been brought to a conclusion, but for a small estate, which common report had endowed with singular qualities, and which was called the “Field of Terror.”

It lay amid the surrounding fields, covered with flowers, and an abundance of rank and luxuriant shrubs, which, while they bore ample testimony to the vigour and fertility of the soil, were equally indicative of the neglect, and desolation, to which it was abandoned. For a long series of years, no ploughshare had penetrated its surface, no seed had been cast upon its furrows; or, if at intervals the attempt was made, the cattle had been invariably seized with phrenzy, had wildly broken from the yoke; and the plough-men and hinds, had rushed from the spot in fright and alarm, affirming, that it was haunted by the most terrific phantoms, who followed the labourer in his duties with a kind of awful familiarity, looking over his shoulders in a manner which no human understanding could bear, and which nothing could prevent from producing delirium and madness.

The question now in dispute was, who should receive this more than suspicious field, as a part of his inheritance. Every man seemed to think, as is the common course of the world, that this self-same spot, which would be useless and of no possible value in his own care, might be extremely applicable, and even advantageous, to his neighbour: and thus the contest, for its right appropriation continued till a late hour of the evening. At length, one of the party proposed a remedy, which, though not directly benefitting any one present, seemed to promise a settlement of the dispute.

“By a codicil in the will,” said he, “we are enjoined to shew some mark of kindness, to a poor relation of the testator, who lives hard by in the village. It is true, the girl is very distantly related to us; and there can be no doubt that portionless as she is, she will yet procure a warm man for her husband, for she is a clever, frugal lass, and the people call her the pretty Sabina. Suppose, we give up this “Field of Terror” to her; we shall at once get rid of the testator’s injunction; and to say the truth, it is no inconsiderable gift, provided she gets a husband who knows how to go the right way to work with it.” The others immediately consented to this proposal, and one of the relatives was dispatched to announce the gracious benefaction.

In the mean time, as the twilight began to descend, somebody had knocked at Sabina’s door, and to her question of “Who’s there?” a reply was given, which had the instant effect of withdrawing the bolt of her little bed-room window. It was a voice long and anxiously sighed for, the voice of her faithful Constantine; who, poor as herself, had two years before joined a regiment on foreign service, in the hope of facilitating a union with his beloved Sabina, whose heart filled with the purest affection, was entirely devoted to him.

It was a beautiful sight to see the joy which lighted up the lovely countenance of Sabina, as her eyes diffused in tears, her face covered with smiles, appeared through the winding branches of columbine which grew before her cottage, and, as the erect and youthful soldier gazed upon her in modest silent bliss, and extended towards her his faithful hand.

“Oh! Constantine,” she exclaimed, in a low and bashful tone of voice, “heaven be praised, that it has sent you once more home again, and living. This has been the burden of all my evening and morning prayers, even when you may not have succeeded in obtaining the hoped for fortune.”

“As for fortune,” replied Constantine, as he shook his head and smiled, “that indeed wears but a very indifferent aspect. Still, it is better than when I went away, and if you but feel courage enough for the undertaking, I fancy we may yet be married, and manage to get through the world in tolerable decency.”

“Faithful Constantine!” ejaculated Sabina, “thus to connect your happiness, with the fortunes of a poor deserted orphan!”

“Come!” my love, said the ardent soldier, “if you can but trust me, say so; give me at once your consent to our union. I assure you, things will not run so badly with us; we shall be happy in each other, and, with such a foundation, we may yet live like princes.”

“And have you obtained your discharge? Are you really no longer a soldier? Is the war at an end?”

“Why as for that,” rejoined her lover, “the matter, at present, is hardly decided in either way. The peace is not in fact concluded, but then, the war is quite at a stand; and on this account, my colonel has thought it right to disband his regiment.”

Sabina now extended her hand to her eager lover, in all the joy of youthful, ardent affection, and permitted her future bridegroom to enter the cottage. The youthful pair were speedily seated, and Constantine informed his mistress, that he had obtained his small stock of wealth from an Italian prisoner, whom he had captured on the field of battle, and who had paid this, as the price of his liberty and his life. Sabina, as she turned her wheel, listened with deep attention to her lover’s recital, bestowing, from time to time, a smile of fond approbation upon his conduct; and inwardly rejoicing, that no reproach could hereafter be thrown upon their slender means, thus honourably acquired.

Their conversation was now interrupted by the appearance of the messenger, dispatched by Sabina’s relations. Covered with blushes, and in a faltering voice, the modest girl presented her destined bridegroom to the stranger; and the latter replied:

“Why then, it would seem, as if I had been sent most opportunely; for if your betrothed lover has brought no very considerable share of wealth with him from the wars, the addition which I am commissioned to offer, in the name of the collected heirs to your relation’s property, cannot but be a welcome gift; and it was indeed enjoined us, by the testator’s will, that we should remember you in a handsome way.”

There was something too much of arrogance, in the manner in which this piece of good fortune was tendered, to please the lofty spirit of Constantine. But the humble Sabina, wholly ignorant of the mode in which her relatives had evinced their generosity, received the communication as a special interposition of Providence, and could only hold down her head, while her face was covered with a smile of heart-felt, grateful joy. But, as soon as she heard that the “Field of Terror” was the promised boon, with which her claim was to be liquidated, the base injustice of her relations pressed to her heart, with a painful sickening coldness; and she felt it impossible to restrain the overflowing tears of disappointed hope. Her relation, with a smile of half-suppressed contempt, expressed his regret, that she should have allowed herself to expect more than her friends had thought right to allot her; “And indeed,” he observed, “this is a much larger proportion of the inheritance, than you could fairly hope to receive.”

With this speech, he was about to retire, but Constantine threw himself in his way; and with that intrepid coolness, which so frequently attends a mind conscious of its own superiority, he said: “Sir! I perceive, that you and your fellows, have been pleased to convert the benevolent intentions of the deceased, into mere derision and mockery; and that it is your joint resolve to withhold a single shilling of his property, from the worthy girl who is now my bride elect. We shall still accept your proffered boon, in the full confidence, that, under the guidance of Heaven, this dreaded “Field of Terror,” may be productive of more advantages in the hands of an honest soldier, than can enter the imaginations of such a groveling, selfish set of poltroons.”

The messenger, who felt rather uneasy at the tone and manner assumed by the young soldier, did not hazard a reply; and with an altered countenance, hurried out of the cottage.

Constantine now kissed away the tears from Sabina’s cheeks, and hastened on the wings of joy, to fix with the curate, an early day of marriage.

After a few weeks, Constantine and Sabina were married; and entered upon their humble mode of house-keeping. The money brought from the wars was chiefly expended in the purchase of a fine yoke of oxen; part of the remainder was invested in seed and necessary articles of household furniture; and the rest reserved for daily expenditure to be doled out in the most economical manner, till the harvest of the succeeding year should replenish their stores. But, as Constantine drove his cattle and plough to the field of labour, he looked back upon Sabina with a smiling countenance, and assured her, he was now going to sow the real seed of gold, which another year would restore with two-fold bounty. Sabina could only follow him with her anxious looks, and wish, in her heart, that he were once safely returned from the detested “Field of Terror.”

It is true, he returned home, and that long before the vesper-bell had sounded; but far from being so joyful, as in the native confidence of his heart, he had promised himself in the morning. He dragged laboriously after him the fragments of his shattered plough; before him paced with difficulty, one of his oxen sorely maimed; and marks of blood were seen on his own head and shoulder. But he bore up under his numerous misfortunes, with a sound and even cheerful heart; and consoled with undiminished spirit, the grief of his weeping Sabina. “Come,” said he, with a smile, “get your pickling tubs in order; for the goblin who reigns in the “Field of Terror,” has made us a present of a large quantity of beef. The beast I brought home with me has so injured himself in his phrenzy, that he will never more be fit for labour; and, as for the other, he darted off into the mountains, where I had the joy of seeing him cast himself into the torrent, from whence he will never again make his appearance.”

“Oh, my relations! my wicked relations,” sobbed the disconsolate Sabina. “They have not only deprived you, by their pernicious donation, of the little property for which you so sorely travailed; but they have also covered you with wounds, and crippled your strength.”

“That is an affair of but little consequence,” rejoined the intrepid Constantine. “The beasts managed to get me between them, just as their fury had reached its summit; and I was determined not to relinquish my hold. But, Heaven be praised! things might have gone a great deal worse with me; and in the morning, I will be in the field again.”

Sabina used every means in her power, to dissuade her husband from his resolution; but he only replied, by saying; that so long as he could move an arm or a leg, the field should not lie idle. “If we cannot plough it, we will dig it: and I am no timid beast of labour, but a tried and dauntless soldier, over whom a goblin can have no power.” He now slaughtered the wounded ox; cut it in pieces; and, on the following morning, while Sabina was busied in preparing it for pickle, pursued his road of the previous day, scarcely less alert and cheerful than then, though now obliged to handle the hoe and spade, instead of guiding his oxen, and well mounted plough.

This time, he returned rather late in the evening, rather pale and exhausted; but full of spirits, and soon capable of tranquilizing his agitated wife.

“This kind of labour makes one weary,” said he, with a smile; “for there is a sort of goblin fellow stands constantly beside me; sometimes in one form and sometimes in another, and mocks me both with word and deed; but he seems to feel no little surprize, that I give no heed to his pranks; and, it is this which fills me with fresh courage. Besides, these kind of creatures have no power over an honest man, who is labouring in his vocation.”

This continued for many days together. The persevering Constantine, pursued, without interruption, his daily labour of digging, sowing, and eradicating the weeds and useless plants which had overspread the field. It is true, the slow process of the spade, only enabled him to cultivate a small portion of the estate; but this served to make him the more zealous and industrious in his occupation; and he, at length, saw a crop spring up, which promised, and eventually produced, a sufficient, if not an abundant harvest. Even the toil of reaping, and transporting it from the field to the barn, was thrown entirely upon his own shoulders; for the labourers in the vicinity would not have engaged, for any consideration, in spending a day upon the dreaded “Field of Terror;” and he would, on no account, permit Sabina to lend her assistance, since her advanced state of pregnancy, led him to hope for that increase of his family, with which she shortly presented him.

The child was born, and in three years an addition was made of two more, without any change in the worldly circumstances of Constantine. By perseverance and undiminished zeal, he continued to force from the fearful “Field of Terror” an annual extension of produce, and thus redeemed his pledge to Sabina of bringing her through all her difficulties like an honest man.

One evening in autumn, as the shade of night began to set in, and Constantine was still busied with his spade, a tall robust man, of unusual size of limb, black and sooty as a charcoal-burner, and holding a furnace poker in his hand, appeared suddenly before him, and said: “Are there no cattle to be had in this part of the country, that you thus labour away with your two hands? One would suppose, by the extent of your landmarks, that you were a wealthy farmer.” Constantine was perfectly aware of the stranger’s character, and treated him in the same cool way, with which he usually received the goblin of the field. He remained silent, endeavoured to withdraw his attention from the figure before him to his work, and laboured on with double ardour. But the swarthy visitor, instead of disappearing, as was the usual practice of the goblin, to present himself again in a more frightful and alarming form, remained where he stood, and in a friendly tone continued: “My good fellow, you are doing both yourself and me injustice by this line of conduct. Give me an honest and candid answer. Perhaps I may know of a remedy for your ills.”

“Well then,” rejoined Constantine, “in Heaven’s name be it so. If you should but cajole me with these friendly words, the fault will be at your door and not at mine.”

With this he began to relate the whole story of his adventures since he had taken possession of the field. He gave an undisguised recital of his first distress, a faithful representation of his just and honest indignation against the goblin who haunted his property, and detailed the difficulty he found under such continual interruption and provocation, of supporting his family by the mere application of his hoe and spade.

The stranger gave an attentive ear to the narrative, seemed lost in thought for a few minutes, and then broke forth in the following address:

“I see, my good fellow, that you know who I am; and I look upon it as a proof of your frank and manly disposition, that you have made no concealment, that you have spoken out boldly of the displeasure you entertain towards me. To say the truth, you certainly have had sufficient cause; but in thus putting your mettle to the test, I will make a proposal which may indemnify you for a good deal of the past. It sometimes happens that, when I have fairly exhausted myself in wild and fantastic tricks, through wood, and field, and mountain, I begin to fancy I should like to attach myself to some quiet family, that I may live for half a year or so, a peaceful orderly life. What do you say to taking me for six months as your servant?”

“It is not right, from people of your sort,” said Constantine, “to pass your jokes upon an honest man, who reposes confidence in you.”

“No! no!” replied the other, “there is no joke in it; it is my serious intention. You will find in me a sturdy, active servant; and, as long as I live with you, not a single spirit or spectre will venture to shew himself on the “Field of Terror,” so that you may admit whole herds of cattle to brouze upon it.”

“I should like the thing well enough,” rejoined Constantine, “if I were but sure that you would keep your word; and above all, that I were doing right in making the engagement.”

“That must be your own affair,” said the stranger; “but I have never broken my word since these Ogre mountains have stood, and a mere creature of evil and malice I certainly am not. A little merry and wild and mischievous sometimes I own—but that is all!”

“Why I almost believe,” said Constantine, “that you are the celebrated Number-nip.”

“Harkee!” cried the stranger, with a frown, “if that be your opinion, I would also have you to know, that the mighty spirit of the mountains cannot endure that name; and that he chuses to call himself the Lord of the Hills.”

“That would be an odd sort of a servant whom I must call my Lord of the Hills;” said Constantine, in a tone of raillery.

“You may call me Forester then,” rejoined his companion. Constantine looked awhile on the earth, pondering upon the course he should adopt, and at length exclaimed:

“Well! agreed! I can hardly do amiss in accepting your services. I have often seen a poor senseless brute drilled into domestic use, by carrying parcels, turning spits and other household duties—why not a goblin?”

His new servant burst into a hearty laugh at this observation, and said: “I must acknowledge such an estimate was never before made of one of my family. But I am not the less pleased with it, so give me your hand my honoured master.”

Constantine made a further condition, that his new servant was, on no account, to inform Sabina or the children of his connexion with the “Field of Terror,” or rather of his descent from the caverns and shafts of the Ogre mountains; nor was he, on any occasion, to exhibit any of his fearful goblin tricks about the house or court-yard; and, as Forester promised all that was required of him with every token of good faith, the bargain was soon at an end, and they now proceeded home.

Sabina, after a time, wondered at the increasing prosperity of their domestic economy; and was not wholly free from feelings of secret dread at their swarthy gigantic assistant. At first the children never ventured outside the door, when they perceived him at work in the yard or garden; but, by degrees, his friendly industrious habits gained upon them all; and when he occasionally indulged in a fit of fantastic merriment, by chasing the dog or the poultry round the house, it was considered more amusing than surprising; and a single look from Constantine was, at any time, sufficient to bring him within the proper limits of order. In full reliance upon the promises of the mountain spirit, Constantine applied the slender savings of many years to the purchase of a fresh yoke of oxen; and with his newly amended plough drove to the field in the highest glee. Sabina looked after him with an anxious sorrowful countenance, and with an equally anxious mind awaited his return in the evening, fearing a renewal of the same disaster, the same disappointed hopes, or that his personal injuries, this time, might be more dangerous and alarming than before. But with the sound of the vesper-bell, Constantine came singing through the village, driving his sleek well fed yoke before him, kissed his wife and children in the fulness of his joy, and shook his servant cordially by the hand.

Forester now frequently went to the field alone, while Constantine remained behind engaged about the yard or garden. A considerable piece of the “Field of Terror” was cleared for cultivation; and, to the great astonishment of the village neighbours, and the equal discontent and envy of Sabina’s selfish relations, every thing assumed an air of prosperity and comfort. It is true, Constantine, when alone, often reflected that all this could be but of short duration, “and Heaven knows” he exclaimed, “how I shall manage with the harvest; for Forester’s time will then be out, and the goblin of the field may chuse to appear with replenished spirits.” But he considered that the gathering in of the crop was a labour which, of itself, gave additional vigour to the workman’s arm and heart; and it was possible that Forester, for old acquaintance sake, might keep the land free from guests; as in fact, at times of cheerful relaxation, the latter seemed to imply.

In the course of time, the needful labours of the field were completed. Winter arrived, and Constantine daily drove to the forest for a stock of fuel and wood. On one of these days it so chanced that Sabina was entreated to visit a poor widow in the village, who lay dangerously ill; and whom, as far as their increasing means admitted, Constantine and his wife, had been accustomed to relieve. She was at a loss how to dispose of the children during her absence, but Forester offering his services, with whose stories the children were always delighted, and with whom they were ever pleased to remain, she proceeded on her charitable purpose without further hesitation.

About an hour after her departure, Constantine returned from the forest; and having disposed of his waggon in the out-house, and prepared the stall for his cattle; he proceeded towards the house to revive his numbed and frozen limbs by the blaze of a cheerful fire. On approaching the door, his ear was saluted by a cry of painful distress from his children. He darted into the house, and, on entering the sitting-room, found the children creeping behind the stove, and crying aloud for help, while Forester was wildly jumping about the room with shouts of violent laughter, making the most hideous and disgusting faces, and with a crown of sparks and fiery rays playing about his head.

“What is all this?” said Constantine, in a tone of indignant anger, and the supernatural decorations of Forester’s head disappeared; his fantastic merriment instantly ceased, and he began to excuse himself with great humility for thus trying to amuse the children. But the children ran towards their father, complaining that Forester had first of all told them a number of most horrific stories, and that then he had assumed a variety of frightful disguises, sometimes appearing with the head of a ram, sometimes with that of a dog.

“Enough! enough!” exclaimed Constantine. “Away, sirrah! you and I no longer remain under the same roof.” With this he seized Forester by the arm, and shoved him violently out of the house, desiring the children to remain quietly in the room, and to dismiss their fears.

Forester suffered all this without uttering a single word of expostulation; but, as soon as he found himself alone with Constantine in the open court, he said with a smiling countenance: “I hope, master, we shall make the matter up. I know I have done a very foolish thing, but I assure you it shall never happen again. Somehow or other the old mad fit came upon me and I forgot myself.”

“For that very reason, because you can forget yourself,” rejoined Constantine, “we part. You might terrify my children into a paroxysm of phrenzy, and, as I have said, our contract here terminates.”

“My time is not up;” said Forester, in a dogged tone, “I will go into the house.”

“Not a step further—at your peril!” cried Constantine. “You have broken the agreement by your cursed goblin tricks, and all that I can do is to pay you your full wages. Here, take it and pack yourself off.”

“My full wages?” said the mountain-spirit, with a sneer of bitter contempt. “Have you never seen my stores of gold in the caverns of yonder hills?”

“I do this more on my own account than yours,” said Constantine, “no man shall call me his debtor.” And so saying, he forced the money into his servant’s pocket.

“And what is to be done with the Field of Terror?” enquired Forester, in a solemn but almost ireful tone.

“That which it may please God:” rejoined Constantine. “Twenty fields of terror are of no importance to me in comparison with the safety of a single hair of my poor children’s heads. Take yourself away, or I shall give you that, you will long have cause to remember!”

“Gently!” cried the mountain-spirit, “gently! my friend. When any of my family condescend to assume a human form, they chuse one of rather stern materials. You might chance to get an under birth in this same fray, and in that case Heaven be merciful unto you!”

“That it has ever been,” said Constantine, “and has also given me a frame of no slender power. Away to your mountains, disgusting monster! I now warn you for the last time.”

Excited by this reproach to a pitch of violent fury, Forester sprang upon Constantine, and an obstinate fight ensued. They struggled about the yard for a considerable time, each using every means in his power to overthrow his adversary, without victory declaring herself upon either side; till at length Constantine, by his superior skill in wrestling, managed to bring his opponent to the earth, and having placed his knee upon the chest of his fallen foe, began to pummel him most furiously, exclaiming: “I’ll teach you to attack your master, my precious Lord of the Hills.”

The Lord of the Hills, however, laughed so heartily at this address, that Constantine conceiving his manly efforts to be the subject of derision, only laid on with redoubled vigour, till at length the former exclaimed: “For God’s sake hold! I am not laughing at you, I am laughing at myself and I humbly beg your pardon!”

“That is another sort of affair,” said Constantine, as he rose up and assisted his conquered adversary to regain his legs.

“I have now learnt what human life is, from the very foundation upwards,” said the latter, still continuing his noisy laughter. “I doubt if any of my kindred have ever pursued the study so profoundly. But harkee! my good fellow, you must admit that I carried on the war in an honourable way. For as you will see yourself, I might with ease have called in half a dozen mountain-spirits to my assistance, though amidst all this laughter, I know not how I should have set about it.”

Constantine with a serious air, now looked at the still laughing Number-nip, and said: “It is clear you must entertain a grudge against me, and this will not only be repaid me at the Field of Terror,” but in many an evil chance elsewhere; still I cannot repent of what I have done. I have only exercised a paternal duty on behalf of my children, and were the thing to do over again, I should, on mature reflection, repeat it.”

“No, no!” said Number-nip laughingly, “don’t make yourself uneasy. I have had quite enough for once. Cultivate the Field of Terror from year to year, at your own will and pleasure. I here pass my word that no fearful phantom shall be seen upon it from this day forwards, as long as the Ogre mountains stand. And so fare ye well, my honest, but rigid master!”

With this he gave a friendly nod of adieu, and disappeared; nor was he ever more seen by Constantine. But Number-nip kept his word, and even more. An unusual degree of prosperity attended all the labours of his former employer, and Constantine soon became the richest farmer in the village. And when his children were permitted to play in the “Field of Terror”—a spot which both they and Sabina now visited without the slightest dread, they sometimes related in the evening, that Forester had come to see them, and told them some of his former amusing stories. On such occasions they generally found their pockets filled with either comfits, toys, or pieces of pretty money.

It was a calm, sweet evening, which prevailed in a hilly, woody spot in Schleswig. Klaus, a worker in the coal-mines, came loitering homewards from the scene of his employment, wherein he toiled industriously throughout the week, returning late on a Saturday evening to his family, and his small, but comfortable cottage, accompanying his wife and children to church on the Sabbath, and then early on the Monday morning quitting them to resume his weekly labours. Oh, how delightful were these periods of rest to Klaus and his family! The joy of re-union, enhanced by the intervening six days of separation—the holy duties and solemnities of the Sabbath—the lively humour of the father, and the fund of anecdotes and adventures each had to relate and to hear. The heart of the good man beat more quickly each time when he reached the brow of the little hill from which he caught the first view of the village, and could distinguish the blue smoke from his own cottage chimney, curling gracefully upwards, and announcing to him that his beloved wife was busy preparing some one of his favourite dishes for his supper. ’Tis true that some fears would occasionally mingle with the joy he felt, at the thought of beholding all he loved once more.

“Ah, thou gracious God!” he would murmur to himself, “how much of sorrow and sickness may have fallen on the dear inmates of that humble roof! Who knows but that my wife, who is getting aged now, may not be ill again? Then a stranger will be cooking my supper, and perhaps boiling some herbs for the invalid at the same time; and my good daughter Agnes will be sitting by her mother’s bed-side; and when I enter she will rise, and strive to smile a welcome to me, but cannot for the tears which bedew her face; so she will look away, that I may not see how sad she is. And my little grandson Hans, instead of coming bounding and shouting up, will creep to me, and standing on his toes, whisper, while he slides his little hand into mine, ‘Grandfather, thou must not weep or grieve, otherwise Grannie will be worse, and I shall feel as if my heart were breaking, but must not let them see it!’ Then my dear wife Else will sigh—‘Ah, husband dear, have you not yet heard any news of our beloved son Gotthilf? It is a long and weary time since he departed to seek his fortune as a shoeing-smith,’ and I can only echo her sigh and reply—‘Alas, no!’”

A short time before, such had been the state of things on Klaus’s return, and since then a sad spirit of foreboding had again and again checked the joy with which he ever anticipated his “happy day.” It was now just rising like a cloud over the serenity of his heart; but he knew a spell of potency sufficient to lay the spirit, and folding his hands devoutly, his heart ascended to heaven in silent, wordless prayer, for, as he often said to himself, “What need for words? God understands what I mean far better than I could express it myself.” Scarcely had he thus relieved himself by pious and trustful prayer, than he beheld his little grandson running towards him with outstretched arms. It was easy to perceive that the child was an eager messenger, whether of good or evil remained to be proved, for keenly and anxiously as Klaus gazed on him, he could not in the distance catch the expression of his features. At length the little treble voice reached him: “Sing! shout! rejoice, grandfather! There is news of uncle Gotthilf come—bright, joyous news! And a letter from him, too! And a bearded soldier, with a shining cuirass and helmet, brought the news and the letter, and is sitting in-doors with grandmother and aunt Agnes, telling all about the war. Oh, it is so delightful to listen to him! Let’s make haste, grandfather, or we shall lose all his pretty stories. But sing, grandfather! sing and rejoice!”

But Klaus neither sung and rejoiced, nor hastened onwards, but paused; and as he clasped his hands fervently together, and raised his beaming eyes to heaven, his little grandson was silent for a moment, and thought, “dear grandfather sings and rejoices in his own way; and although I cannot hear him, the angels in heaven surely can!” Then he took hold of Klaus’s hand, and trotted along gaily by his side, making five or six steps to each of the old man’s lengthy strides, and chattering away about the strange soldier—his long, shining sword, which seemed to light up the room, and his great black steed, which had been put in the cow-house, where it kept pawing and striking the ground with its fore-feet, and making such a noise! but never doing the least harm in the world to the cows. Klaus, in his thankfulness to God, gave little heed to the prattle of the child: it was as if a little brook ran murmuring and rippling by his side, soothing and rejoicing his heart by its music; and yet, though his mind had been absent, his ears had caught and retained some of the words; for, as he entered his dwelling, the soldier, who sat eating and drinking so comfortably between his wife and daughter, did not appear to him a stranger, but rather an old acquaintance, and extending his hand to him, he exclaimed, “This is kind of you to bring me news of my dear son: how we have longed for tidings of him! Welcome! a thousand times welcome to my home!”

The soldier accepted this greeting as heartily as it was given, and conducted himself exactly as if he had been at home, and drew a little on one side, in order to make room for the arm-chair of the master of the house.

Else and her daughter greeted Klaus affectionately, and when they had served up his favourite dish, and set a foaming jug of clear, golden-looking beer by his side, they requested the soldier to repeat his gratifying intelligence: “for,” exclaimed Else, with sparkling and moistened eyes, “one cannot hear such glad tidings too often; no, not if it was repeated again and again unto eternity;” and she seated herself at her spinning-wheel as she spoke, Agnes followed her example, while Hans stationed himself close by the stranger, looking eagerly up into his face, and seeming as if he would fain catch each word, even before it was uttered.

The soldier, addressing Klaus, said: “Fortune has guided your brave son’s steps. After wandering through many distant lands, and visiting many strange towns, where he took every opportunity of improving himself in his trade, chance led him to a spot where a great hunt was held by our most gracious sovereign Christian, King of Denmark.” As he pronounced this name, the soldier touched his helmet, as if saluting an officer, and the old man raised his cap and bowed his head. “The cheerful sound of the horns, the voices of the hounds, and the calls of the huntsman, fell so pleasantly on the ears of your son, that, loath to lose them, he penetrated further and further into the windings of the woody valley. Suddenly the hunted stag crossed his path, and vanished again in another thicket; close at its heels came a stately rider, mounted on a white horse, which he spurred at a high thicket. The noble steed attempted the tremendous leap, but his fore-legs caught the top of the fence; he fell heavily, and his rider was flung, head foremost, out of the saddle to a considerable distance; both horse and man lay motionless, and to all appearance dead. Your son ran up immediately, and raising the biped shook him well, and brought him to his senses in this rough manner. The first use he made of them was to inquire, with flashing eyes and a voice of thunder, ‘what this meant?’ ‘Why, that you would have been suffocated by the sudden rush of blood to the head, if you had not happened to have had a rough fellow like me at hand,’ was Gotthilf’s reply, and with this he turned his attention to the quadruped, got it once more on its legs, arranged the bridle and saddle, held the stirrups for the rider to mount, and then walked silently off, without paying the slightest attention to the words or questionings of the man he had helped, who was now sensible how much he owed him.”

“Ha ha! that is just like my brave Gotthilf,” exclaimed the pleased old man, “ever ready to render assistance in time of need, but haughty as an emperor if offended. Well, continue.”

“Some days afterwards,” continued the soldier, “as your son was entering Copenhagen, he heard it proclaimed, that whoever could cure the king’s favourite horse of a bad lameness should receive a very considerable sum. Gotthilf inquired his way to the royal stables, and when, at his request, the animal was shown to him, what was his astonishment on perceiving it to be the very same white horse which he had seen fall in the valley. But this discovery troubled him little either way; his business there was to discover the cause and seat of the lameness, and see if he could do anything with it. Accordingly, he examined it very carefully, and presently declared that it did not, as was supposed, arise from any disease of the fetlock, but from a bruise in the sole of the foot, which he undertook to cure thoroughly in a fortnight. The wise ones who had previously examined the horse raised a great outcry at this bold declaration, pronouncing Gotthilf a quack, a pretender, and what not; but as they were unable themselves to cure the lameness, the animal was handed over to him; and, sure enough, at the expiration of the fortnight it was perfectly sound. When your son led the horse out before the king, the latter recognised him as the sturdy fellow who had been of such service to him on the day of the hunt, and, smiling, said: ‘If you are a real living being, and not that fabulous smith, Wolundar, so celebrated in ancient legend for his sorcery and his evil temper, I would fain retain you in my service.’

“‘I am willing, your Majesty,’ replied Gotthilf, bowing reverently; ‘I am no sorcerer, but a christian, and a member of that evangelical church for which you have fought so zealously in Germany, and your Majesty’s true and loyal servant.’

“‘Would my endeavours had been more successful,’ sighed the king.

“‘We cannot command success,’ said your son, ‘it was a good and glorious battle for a righteous cause. And now we have a glorious peace throughout the whole land.’

“‘Thou art my man!’ exclaimed King Christian, extending his hand to Gotthilf, who clasped it cordially and yet respectfully; I stood by at the time, and we all, nobles and peasants, bond and free, rejoiced with your brave son, who has ever since accompanied his sovereign, and is at once smith, armourer, huntsman, and all that requires bravery and devotion. But he will not promise to remain at court for good, but declares his intention of returning home to you, and practising his trade here in Schleswig, and feeding his furnace with your coals.”

“Yes—yes,” said Klaus, “so I hoped, so he promised. Wander about, my son,” said I to him, when we parted, “as long as you find pleasure in doing so, or can learn anything good or useful; but forget not your family. Home, and especially a home in the heart, is far more precious than gold.”

“And when will my darling son return to us?” asked Else, while the rosy lips of Agnes moved as if they uttered the same words, although no sound reached the ear.

“Most likely he tells you in his letter,” replied the soldier, pointing to a sealed letter which lay on the table.

“How’s this, Mother,” said Klaus to his wife, “you have not opened it!”

“It was addressed to you, dear husband, and not to me,” replied Else.

Klaus nodded approvingly, but said—“Husband and wife are one, especially in matters relating to a beloved and absent son.” He opened the letter, and read it attentively through, while the soldier said to Else and her daughter: “This much I know, that Gotthilf will only attend his royal master in one more campaign before he returns home to settle among you, and that one will not last long. It is merely undertaken to quell an insurrection of the Dithmarsens, that strange tribe, who, although they have called themselves to the crown of Denmark, choose to be governed by laws of their own, and who have just discovered that some antiquated old rights are interfered with, and, consequently, are up in arms against the injustice, as they term it. But our army will soon settle all points of law for them, and convince them that might is right. Then you will have Gotthilf returning to you victorious.”

“God forbid!” said Klaus solemnly, as he slowly folded up the letter, and placed it carefully in the breast pocket of his waistcoat. The others stared at him in astonishment, and the soldier said: “Did your exclamation apply to my words?”

“Yes and no,” replied the old man, smiling, “it was applicable to your words, and it was uttered in reference to the end of this letter.”

“There is no bad news, I trust,” exclaimed the mother, anxiously.

“None relative to our son, good wife, for he is not answerable for the evil which others meditate; but there is bad news relating to persons very dear to every loyal heart, and to one in particular.” He was silent for some minutes, and at length drawing a deep breath like one from whose bosom a heavy burden had been suddenly removed, he smiled and murmured—“Aye, well, it is not my place to give an opinion in such matters;” and immediately began to talk on a variety of subjects, like one who would fain drive away some intruding thought; but every now and then came pauses, and he sunk into reverie. His wife and daughter ventured not to inquire further, for they well knew that when he deemed it proper to communicate aught to them, it was done frankly and at once; but that at other times his bosom resembled some casket fastened with a skilfully devised lock, the key to which had been lost, and so well did they know him that they then never even dreamed of questioning him.

The evening passed away in cheerful converse, and on the morrow the soldier set forth on his journey, expressing his obligations for their hospitality, and accompanied by their good wishes, and many thanks for having brought tidings of the loved and absent son. The family then entered on all the solemn duties of the sabbath as usual, Klaus appearing to enter into them with more than usual seriousness and fervency. The minister of the little church which they attended had chosen for his theme the folly and wickedness of those who having put their hand to the plough afterwards drew back, and the rewards held out to those who were faithful in well-doing.

The countenance of the good old Klaus became more serious as he drank in each word, and when the service was over, sinking on his knees, he prayed so long that his wife was obliged to touch his shoulder gently, and remind him that the church was empty. As they walked homewards he was silent and thoughtful, but looked joyous and confident. Immediately after dinner he began to fasten up his bundle, and asked his wife for his allowance of eatables and drinkables. “Surely you are not going back to the forest to-night, dear husband?” said Else; “why not stay with us as usual until to-morrow morning?”

“No, I go not to the forest, but farther, much father,” replied Klaus. “If you have any message for your son, good wife, or you Agnes for your brother, or my little Hans for his uncle, give it to me at once, for in another hour I shall be on my way to Copenhagen.”

“On a Sunday evening!” exclaimed Else; “will not that be desecrating the Sabbath?”

“’Tis God calls me,” was the reply: “God and my conscience; nor have I any time to lose. Be not anxious, my dear ones; I hope with confidence that the Great Being who has inspired me with this purpose, will lead me home again safely and joyfully. If all goes as I think, as I trust it will, I shall bring our Gotthilf back with me. Should I fail—but there—let us trust in that Providence by whom even the hairs on our heads are numbered.

The little circle were astonished at this unlooked-for journey; but confidence in Heaven, and in the upright firmness of the old man, supported them. In another hour Klaus was striding manfully on, his eyes somewhat dimmed by a tear of affection, while weeping and yet hopeful his family gazed after his departing form, until it was lost in the distance.

A short time after the occurrence of the scenes which we have already narrated, a crowd of people stood assembled round the gates of the royal palace of Copenhagen, waiting to see their king ride out. The noble white steed was already there, richly caparisoned, and held by Gotthilf, who, since he had cured the animal, allowed no one to tend him but himself.

Christian had just crossed the threshold, attired with simple yet costly elegance, and as he grasped the pummel of his saddle, said: “What ails my brave smith to-day? Why, Gotthilf, you seem strangely moved.”

“May it please your Highness, I have just perceived my old father standing among the crowd. I cannot imagine what has brought him hither. Something good, I am convinced, for all his actions are carefully ordered.”

“Call him hither,” said the King; and, on a sign from Gotthilf, old Klaus came forward. Gotthilf was endeavouring by motions to make his father understand that his first duty was to pay homage to the king; but his care was needless, for at that moment the whole world appeared to contain no other individual for Klaus but his sovereign. Reverentially and with uncovered head did the old miner draw near to the prince, his looks expressing cheerful confidence. “God has ordained this!” he said, “’Tis he who has thus brought me at once into the presence of my sovereign, and he will doubtless now inspire me with words in which to express to you what I have in my heart. The subject is most important, my liege.”

“Does it concern thy brave son?” inquired the prince.

“Higher, far higher, my king,” replied Klaus.

“Thyself, then, perchance?”

“Higher, far higher.”

“Indeed, then, perhaps it relates to me, your sovereign?”

“Partly. But still I must once more repeat—higher, far higher, gracious king.”

“O ho!” said the prince, laughing, “Be it known unto thee, good miner Klaus, that if your errand relates to the Emperor of Germany, or the Pope, I do not acknowledge their supremacy.”

“Nor do I, gracious sire,” replied Klaus, “I am your subject, and yours only; and you are subject only to God: what, then, have we to do with Emperors or Popes?”

The king looked approvingly at him, and said: “Needs thy business haste?”

“Perhaps each moment is fraught with important consequences both for time and eternity,” said Klaus, solemnly.

King Christian turned to the smith, and said: “Well, then, brave Gotthilf, take thou my noble steed, which I owe to thy care and skill, back to his stall; I will not ride to-day, but hear thy father’s errand.” With this he greeted the assembled crowd courteously, and re-entered the palace, accompanied by the old miner, while the people marvelled and wondered.

Arrived in his private cabinet, Christian seated himself in an arm-chair of purple velvet, embroidered with gold, and Klaus stood reverentially before him.

“Now,” said the King, “thou requirest rest far more than I do; I was merely going out riding for the sake of exercise and health, but thou hast performed a long and tedious pilgrimage. Draw a chair hither, and seat thyself.”

“My liege,” replied Klaus, “lead not your subject into temptation. What though I have been brought up in forest wilds, I know full well that it becomes not me to seat myself in the presence of my sovereign as I would before an equal. And had I not previously known this, your kingly presence would have impressed it on me. Yes, great king, you are a man consecrated by God, and entrusted with great power and heavy responsibilities.”

“Heavy responsibilities, indeed!” murmured Christian, as if unconsciously, and then added—“True, true, good Klaus; I have often felt this most deeply. I observe that thou makest use of far more impressive words than are generally employed by persons in thy station. I am about to call for a cup of wine, and hope that thou wilt not refuse to take one with me.” He pulled the bell, and commanded the page who attended his summons to bring two cups of Rhenish wine.

“My Lord and King,” said the miner, as the page bowed and withdrew, “although my most costly drink, when at home, is wont to consist of a draught of hop-beer, I will not deny that I shall right willingly taste a cup of good old wine; especially as I shall have the honour of doing so in the presence and companionship of your most gracious majesty. But with your approbation, I will first discharge my errand, and then quaff the good liquor. Work first and pleasure afterwards.”

At this moment the page returned, bearing on a silver waiter two richly embossed golden cups filled with sparkling wine, and kneeling before the king proffered it to him.

“Set them on yon table by the window, my son, and leave us,” observed Christian; and when they were again alone the following conversation took place between the king and the miner:—“Now, brave Klaus, speak thine errand,” said the former.

“My liege, it is said that you meditate invading the territories of the brave Dithmarsens, and have already prepared an army for that purpose. Indeed, my son has written me a letter in which he states the same.”

“For once rumour speaks the truth, then, and thy son has told thee what is a fact, friend Klaus. Do you come as an envoy from the Dithmarsens?”

“No, good my lord, I know no soul among that people; but I know God and his holy laws, and it is in his name that I come, and as his envoy.”

“Wert thou impelled to do so by any vision?”

“My conscience impelled me; which said, ‘Klaus, thy king must not make war on the Dithmarsens.”

“And what business can it possibly be of thy conscience whether I do so or not, man?”

“It would have laid heavily on my conscience if I had suffered you to set off without one word of remonstrance. Now, when I have spoken my thoughts to your Majesty, my conscience will have nothing further to do with the matter.”

“Methinks I can perceive what thou art aiming at, Klaus.”

“And your Majesty does not appear to take my intentions amiss.”

“Mark, then, and confess that I am right. Thou wouldst willingly have thy son at home again, and as he has promised to accompany me in this campaign, thou findest it ill-advised; but we will soon come to good understanding. I will absolve Gotthilf from his promise, and send him home rewarded according to his just merits. Now what hast thou to urge against my projected invasion? How? that shake of the head looks as if thou wert still unsatisfied. Is not all right yet?”

“Far from it, great king. This is not coming to an understanding with one another, but rather to a misunderstanding.”

“Be pleased then, friend Klaus, to state thine own terms of treaty, and let them be better than mine if it is possible.”

“Truth to tell your Majesty, I do not rightly comprehend the meaning of those words, ‘terms of treaty;’ but I will in few and simple words speak my feeling. It is now nearly sixty years since many valuable ancient privileges were wrested from the Dithmarsens by your royal father, by force of arms. They defended themselves manfully, like brave fellows, and much blood was spilt in this strife. That blood resembles the crimson carnation, not only in hue, but also because its pure odour rises up to heaven, for they fought against a tyrant in defence of their hereditary rights; but it rises not as acceptable incense, but calling aloud for vengeance on those who unjustly shed it. Surely this scene is not to be acted over again, and these poor people once again compelled to battle for the few rights tyranny has left them? My king, far be such intentions from you!”

“They are near to me, very near, I do assure thee, good Klaus. But mistake me not, I would but conquer the Dithmarsens in order to be enabled to benefit them when they become my subjects.”

“Were your Majesty a God you might chastise those you loved, in order to perfect them by suffering. But you, although a mighty king, chosen to fill so great an office, are but a man, and the greater your power the greater is your responsibility.”

“Friend Klaus, wilt thou tell me wherefore the Dithmarsens should pretend to claim other and greater rights than those appertaining to you, Schleswigers, and others of my subjects?”

“Because they are your allies, not properly your subjects, but a separate people who voluntarily connected themselves with the kingdom of Denmark. In short, they are different people.”

“Dost consider them better?”

“I consider them different. One coat will not fit every man.”

“’Twere better that it did, Klaus, for then in cases of necessity one might help the other out; and how much of strife and envy this similarity would save.”

“No, no, my liege, begging your pardon, such a state of things would not be better, for then all would resemble each other like so many eggs, and such uniformity would be wearisome to the eye, and productive of endless confusion. Besides, even if these men were enabled to help each other in the matter of dress, there would still be other differences; the great would oppress the small, the fleet would outrun the slow, the strong would triumph over the weak, or they would mutually be of service to each other. How beautiful it is to do good! O, my liege, let me implore you, in the name of the King of kings, suffer the Dithmarsens to wear coats after their own fashion, nor attempt to alter the pattern, or assimilate it to that of your real subjects. Then will your reign be prosperous.”

“I did not stay at home to listen to foolish prosphesies,” angrily exclaimed Christian.

“The prophets of old,” replied Klaus, “were often ignorant men, whose sole merit lay in their simple obedience to the commands of Him who sent them. ’Tis true that I am not gifted with miraculous powers, as they were; but, good my liege, a clear conscience is a priceless gift of God’s, and my conscience will not suffer me to be silent when I think on the invasion you meditate.”

“Very well; and now thou hast satisfied its qualms by telling me so, Miner Klaus, thou canst go thy ways contentedly.”

“Not yet, my lord and sovereign. Tell me, I pray you, is not that large bright sword, which now hangs glittering from your girdle, the same which you drew and used so nobly in Germany in defence of the true faith?”

“It is, friend miner. What of it?”

“Nothing; but methinks, oh king, it were as well, when you set out against the Dithmarsens, to leave that trusty companion behind, and choose some other blade. These apparently inanimate tools often bear a sort of life, when one has employed them, as you did that sword, in a good and noble cause; or in protecting the innocent, as I once did an axe; with it I struck down a wolf that was pursuing my daughter Agnes, and since that time have only used that axe for good purposes, as to add some little comfort to my dwelling, to hew out a cradle for my little grandson, or prepare some pleasant surprise for my good wife. Therefore, leave that sword behind when you set out on this expedition, my liege!”

“Strange man! Well, well, as it becomes not royalty to deny every request offered to it, I will comply. I will leave this sword behind; and I will also leave thy son, unwillingly as I part with him; so thou mayest take him home with thee. Hast thou aught else to ask of me? If so, speak, and it shall be granted.”

“Forgive me, if I decline accepting your Majesty’s offer regarding my son. He is your armourer, your attendant, and cannot leave you at the very period when his services are most required. When danger draws near, a brave man must not flinch from his post. Were he to accept your gracious offer his honour might be blemished.”

“Friend Klaus, if I, his sovereign, choose to dispense with his services, and dismiss him well rewarded, who shall dare to raise a voice against him?”

“Perhaps no one would, my liege. Perhaps many would whisper insinuations which they dared not speak out, and that which is done in secret spreads far; a worm at the root will often destroy a goodly tree; and naught can efface the stain once cast on the pure brightness of a man’s honour; therefore it behoves us to keep it bright and free from each speck of rust, for if at first it be but as a pin’s point it will speedily increase to an unsightly blotch. Besides, even if no one blamed my son, his own conscience would; that still small voice would not fail to whisper, ‘Gotthilf, hadst thou not left thy master, when he went to the wars, such and such an accident might not have befallen him; thy faithful arm might have turned aside the deadly blow, thy skilful care have made his steed more sure-footed.’ And he would feel like a coward who had fled from the battle-field and deserted his standard at the first sound of the trumpet of war, and would no longer have joy in anything on earth, nay, scarcely in God’s blessed word and promises. No, no, great King, you would not have your and my Gotthilf placed in so miserable a plight; that would be a poor recompense for his loyal services; you must not dismiss him until this warfare is at an end. If Gotthilf returns alive, then send him back to me with honour; should he have fallen, then shall we meet again in that world beyond the grave, where all good men shall see salvation. You will take Gotthilf with you, my liege?”

“And canst thou wish me to do so, even while thou dost condemn my entering on this war? Strange, incomprehensible man!”

“Not at all, my liege. A day must come when we shall all appear before the throne of the Most High, to be judged according to our deeds while in the flesh, and to hear the awful fiat, ‘Depart from me, ye workers of iniquity,’ or those blessed words, ‘Enter into the joy of thy Lord.’ Should my son fall in your service, I humbly trust that to him will the latter be addressed, and that my ears shall one day hear them pronounced to me, for I have endeavoured to do my duty, and so do take my leave, great King.”

With these words the old miner bent reverentially to his sovereign, and then strode towards the door; but Christian called out, “Hold, friend Klaus, thou hast not emptied thy cup of wine yet.”

The miner paused. “If your majesty commands, I will do it; but still would pray you to excuse me. Good wine is most refreshing and palateable when it comes after a satisfactorily settled business: the settlement of our business has been by no means satisfactory.”

“Thou art wrong, good Klaus!” exclaimed the king, rising suddenly up and approaching the table on which the cups stood, and taking one himself, he offered the other to the old man. “There now, pledge me in my toast; ‘Peace, protection, and justice, to the brave Dithmarsens, so long as Christian, King of Denmark lives.”

The sturdy old miner fairly trembled with joy. “My King!” he exclaimed, “My great, my good King! I feel as if I must kneel before you, and pay my homage.”

“Now shame on thee, noble old man! Hast forgotten these words—‘Thou shalt kneel to God, and not to man?’”

Klaus knelt down, and folding his hands, exclaimed with deep fervency, “Then to God do I kneel, and most humbly do I thank him that he has inspired my sovereign with such princely, such noble feelings; that he has been pleased to give such power to the words of one of the humblest of his creatures. May he bless and preserve our King to us for many long years, to reign in the hearts of his people; and when at length it is his pleasure to call him from this world, may it be only to exchange a temporal for an eternal crown, and be admitted to the joys of heaven.” Having thus spoken he arose, and, taking the cup from the King’s hand, said, “You have given me an excellent toast, my liege; I will in turn give you one: ‘Long live our gracious monarch, Christian of Denmark!’”

The two men slowly and solemnly emptied their cups, their eyes gazing eagerly the one on the other, and each saw the brightness of the eyes on which he looked dimmed by a tear.

“Thou shalt take that cup with thee, Klaus,” said the King, “and bequeath it to thy descendants.”

“That will I do most willingly, my liege, and the poorest beer drunk out of it will be to me as delicious as this fragrant Rhenish wine.”

“Thou mightest remain with me, and ever have the cup filled with costly wine. I would not suffer thee to want for anything; neither thou, nor any belonging to thee.”

“And in what capacity might it please your Majesty to retain me?”

“Why, let us see. What sayest thee to being my counsellor?”

“No, no, my liege; you have counsellors enough; and it takes a very different man to what I am to fill that office. Yes; I have seen them: they are wise, grave nobles, sometimes pale and haggard with intense study, sometimes rosy and jolly from their devotion to the pleasures of the table; they speak little, look full of meaning, write whole mountains of acts, dress themselves magnificently, and are as anxious about their fine clothes as for the safety of the state. No, no, my gracious liege, old Klaus is not fit for a counsellor,” and he laughed heartily.

The King laughed too, but said, “And yet, old friend, thou hast been my counsellor, and thy words have opened to my gaze clearer views of duty and justice than I had before.”

“I am willing to believe your majesty, but I spoke not of myself. When I entered this chamber I knew not in what terms I should address you; all I knew was, that it was my duty to speak, to warn you that your conscience, nay your hopes of eternal happiness were endangered; but the words were not mine, they were inspired and gifted with power to move your heart.”

“Well then, thou messenger from heaven, remain ever near me to guide and advise.”

“No, my liege, once is as good as a dozen times. The shoemaker must stick to his last. You are called upon to wield a sceptre, or, at times, a sword; I, to use a pick-axe; our paths are far apart; and we have each of us a counsellor, if we will only seek him, one able and willing, not only to guide us aright, but to give us strength to follow that guidance; and we bear ever about with us an infallible mentor, Conscience, whose whispers, if heeded, will not fail to preserve us from sin and all its evils.”

“Farewell then, my good old miner!” said the King; “thou hast indeed left me an invaluable counsellor, one whose admonitions I have hitherto too much disregarded; but henceforth he shall fill the place rejected by thee.”

A few days afterwards the King and the miner parted with every demonstration of friendship. Klaus took back his brave son with him, and great was the joy which greeted their return. Christian and his loyal subject both lived many years after the events here recorded, the one busied in projects of government or war, the other in industry and domestic enjoyment; and neither ever forgot their first interview. Whenever Klaus saw the sabbath closing in—that day devoted by him and his family to the worship of God, and the practice of piety and brotherly love—he was wont to say, “And now hand me the ‘counsellor’s cup;’ we will close this happy day with a draught from it.” And whenever the king had withstood some great temptation, or felt himself in doubt as to his own opinions or the advice of others, he was wont to say, “Let no one disturb me; I am about to consult my faithful counsellor!”